<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An address to those of the Roman communion in England occasioned by the late act of Parliament, for the further preventing the growth of popery.</title>
            <author>Willis, Richard, 1664-1734.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 146 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 85 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66484</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2815</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7811</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12528857</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12528857</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62728</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66484)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62728)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 952:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An address to those of the Roman communion in England occasioned by the late act of Parliament, for the further preventing the growth of popery.</title>
                  <author>Willis, Richard, 1664-1734.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 160 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Mat. Wotton ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Richard Willis. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [3]-[6]</note>
                  <note>Table of contents: p. [7]</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [8]</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Great Britain --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62728:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62728:1"/>
            <p>AN ADDRESS To thoſe of the <hi>Roman Communion</hi> IN ENGLAND: Occaſioned by the late Act of Parliament, For the further Preventing the Growth of Popery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Mat. Wotton,</hi> at the <hi>Three Daggers</hi> near the <hi>Inner-Temple-gate</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:62728:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62728:2"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed for <hi>Matt. Worten,</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>The Second Volume of the Remains of the moſt Reverend Father in God, and Bleſſed Mertyr <hi>William Laud,</hi> Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> Written by himſelf. Collected by the Late Learned M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Henery Wharton,</hi> and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed According to his Requeſt, by the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Mr. <hi>Edmund Wharton</hi> his Father.</item>
               <item>Occaſional Paper, N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Angliae Notitia,</hi> Or the preſent State of <hi>England,</hi> with divers Remarks upon the Ancient State thereof; by <hi>Edward Chamberlayne</hi> Doctor of Laws. The Ninth Edition with Great Additions and Improvements. In Three parts.</item>
               <item>Remaks upon an Eſſay concerning Humane Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, in a <hi>Letter</hi> Addreſſed to the Author. N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 1, 2, 3.</item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of the <hi>Revolution</hi> of <hi>Port<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gal</hi> in the Year 1640. Or an Account of their Revolt from <hi>Spain;</hi> and Setting the Crown on the Heads of <hi>Don John</hi> of <hi>Braganza,</hi> Father to <hi>Don Pedro</hi> the preſent King, and <hi>Catherine</hi> the Queen Dowager of <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Echard</hi>'s <hi>Roman</hi> Hiſtory Firſt and Second Part.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Charone</hi> of Wiſdome, in Three Books. Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by <hi>George Stanhope,</hi> D. D.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Farnaby's</hi> Rhetorik.</item>
               <item>Engliſh Gardiner.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:62728:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62728:3"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed for <hi>Matthew Wot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> at the <hi>Three Daggers</hi> in <hi>Fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>A <hi>Guide to the Devout Chriſtian.</hi> In Three Parts. The Firſt containing Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and Prayers affixed to the days of the Week; Together with many Occaſional Prayers for particular Perſons. The Second for more Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons than one, or a whole Family, for every day of the Week; Together with many Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſional Prayers. The Third containing a Diſcourſe of the Nature and Neceſſity of the Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Together with Meditations thereon, Prayers and Directions for the worthy Receiving thereof. To which is Added. A Prayer for <hi>Aſh-Wedneſday,</hi> or any other time in <hi>Lent;</hi> for <hi>Good-Fryday,</hi> and any Day of Publick Faſting: By <hi>John Inett,</hi> M. A. Chanter of the Cathedral Church of <hi>Lincoln.</hi> The Fourth Edition Corrected.</item>
               <item>A Guide to Repentance, or the Character and Behaviour of the devout Chriſtian in Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; By <hi>John Inett,</hi> Chanter of the Cathedral Church at <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Chriſtians Pattern, or a Treatiſe of the Imitation of Jeſus Chriſt, in Four Books with Cutts, written originally in Latin, by <hi>Thomas à Kempis,</hi> now rendered into Engliſh. To which are added Meditations and Prayers for ſick Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; By <hi>George Stanhope,</hi> D. D. Chaplain in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary to his Majeſty. Price 5<hi>s.</hi> The ſame Book is Printed in a ſmaller Letter and ſold for 2<hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Salvation every Man's great Concern, written originally in French, by Monſieur <hi>Rapin,</hi> done into Engliſh.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:62728:4"/>
               <item>An earneſt Invitation to the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper, wherein all the Excuſes that Men ordinarily make for their not coming to the Holy Communion, are Anſwered, by <hi>Joſ. Glanvil</hi> late Miniſter of <hi>Bath.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Defence of the 39 Articles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> written in Latin by <hi>J. Ellis</hi> S. T. D. now done into Engliſh. To which are added the <hi>Lambeth</hi> Articles, together with the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Bp. <hi>Andrews,</hi> Dr. <hi>Overal,</hi> and other Eminent and Learned Men upon them.</item>
               <item>Twelve Sermons preached upon ſeveral Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; By the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>Richard,</hi> Lord Bp. of <hi>Bath and Wells.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— His 2d. and 3d. Parts of the Demonſtration of the Meſſias, in which the Truth of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion is Defended; eſpecially, againſt the <hi>Jews.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Stanhope</hi>'s Sermon at the Funeral of Dr. <hi>Towerſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— His Sermon preached at the Annual Meeting of the Sons of the Clergy.</item>
               <item>The Heinouſneſs of Injuſtice. A Sermon preached at the Aſſizes at <hi>Lincoln;</hi> by <hi>Lawrence Echard,</hi> A. M.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Bradford</hi>'s Sermon preached before the King. <hi>Jan.</hi> 30th.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Hole</hi>'s Viſitation Sermon at <hi>Bridgwater.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Barton</hi>'s Sermon to the Societies for Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Manners.</item>
               <item>The Character of the True Church, in a Sermon Preach'd at the French Church in the <hi>Savoy,</hi> upon theſe Words, <hi>How goodly are thy Tents O Jacob, and thy Tabernacles O Iſrael,</hi> Numb. 24. ver. 5. by <hi>A. D. Aſtor de Lauſſac,</hi> formerly a Prior and Arch-Deacon of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:62728:4"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS</head>
            <list>
               <item>THE Deſign of this Addreſs, <hi>Page</hi> 1.</item>
               <item>Why thoſe of the <hi>Roman Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> have not Reaſon to expect the ſame Toleration with other Diſſenters, <hi>p.</hi> 4.</item>
               <item>Reaſons to perſuade thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to examine the Grounds of their Religion. <hi>p.</hi> 15.</item>
               <item>Of the Infallibility of the Church of <hi>Rome. p.</hi> 25.</item>
               <item>Of Tranſubſtantiation. <hi>p.</hi> 54.</item>
               <item>Of the Idolatry of the Church of <hi>Rome. p.</hi> 95.</item>
               <item>Of the Popes Supremacy <hi>p.</hi> 127.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:62728:5"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 10 in Marg. after Vid. ad 4 <hi>Gen.</hi> p. 13. line 10. for they, read <hi>the Romaniſts;</hi> p. 27. l. 11. f. it r. <hi>is.</hi> p. 28. l. 16. f. differs r. <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer.</hi> p. 32. l. 14. f. pretences r. <hi>pretenders.</hi> p. 55. l. <hi>ult.</hi> f. thing and lies r. <hi>things and lie.</hi> p. 57. l. 9. f. terms r. <hi>forms.</hi> p. 58. l. 9. after <hi>Now</hi> r. <hi>our Saviour.</hi> p. 60. l. 21. f. bleſſings r. <hi>bleſſing.</hi> p. 117. l. 16. f. Scripture r. <hi>Scriptures</hi> and <hi>dele</hi> adds. p. 126. l. 5. f. thoſe r. <hi>theſe.</hi> p. 141. l. <hi>penult.</hi> f. Perſon r. <hi>Perſons.</hi> p. 143. l. 1. after and r. <hi>the.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="address">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62728:5"/>
            <head>AN ADDRESS To thoſe of the <hi>Roman Communion</hi> IN ENGLAND.</head>
            <p>THE Deſign of this Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs is not by any means to inſult over you; in the Circumſtances under which it has pleaſed God in his Providence to bring you; or to raiſe popular Odium againſt you. No, however neceſſary I may judge
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62728:6"/> that which has lately been done, yet I cannot but have a great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion for any thing that looks like Suffering for Conſcience ſake. And this, I think, I owe not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Principles of Humane Nature, which require that we ſhould have a tenderneſs and pity for thoſe that are in Affliction; but to the Principles of my Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as a Chriſtian and a Member of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> I have always looked upon it as one of the Glories of the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that it gives the dominion over Mens Conſciences to God on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; that it aſſerts the natural Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Mankind to judge for themſelves what it is that God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects from them; that it makes very charitable Allowances for the Ignorance and Miſtakes of Men when joined with Sincerity and a true Love of God; and that in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62728:6"/> conſequence of theſe things it does not incline it's Members to a ſevere inquiſition into the private Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Men, or to be hard upon them upon that account. And on the other ſide, that it has been a great aggravation of the Errors of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of them has been ſo rigidly exacted, under no leſs pain than <hi>Damnation</hi> in the other World, and the being <hi>Burnt,</hi> or at leaſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndone</hi> in this, whenever it has been in their power to effect it.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay perhaps, That if the Opinion of Proteſtants be ſo much againſt Perſecution, how comes it to paſs that there have been ſo many ſevere Laws from time to time made againſt you; eſpecially <hi>this laſt,</hi> which deprives your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of their Inheritance, if they will not renounce their Religion;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62728:7"/> and deprives you of the comfort and aſſiſtance of your Spiritual Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by forbidding them to Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe any Office of their Function under pain of lying in a Goal all their Lives if they are caught?</p>
            <p>Now in anſwer to this, I would not aggravate Matters to make you odious; but as plainly, and as ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly as I can, lay the Reaſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you which, we may ſuppoſe, the Nation went upon in making theſe Laws, in ſome hopes to alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate that Exaſperation which your preſent Sufferings may cauſe, and which may very likely make you throw away, without conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, all that a Proteſtant can ſay for your Conviction.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Why thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion have not reaſon to expect the ſame Toleration with other Diſſenters.</note> 
               <hi>And Firſt,</hi> I deſire
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62728:7"/> you would conſider that there muſt be ſome peculiar Reaſon of this dealing with you under a <hi>Prince,</hi> and in a <hi>Nation</hi> ſo much inclined to Liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in almoſt every Body elſe. We have indeed, a very ill O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of your Errors, and the danger of them to the Souls of Men; and of the diſhonour brought to God by giving to Creatures the Worſhip due only to him. But beſides theſe, there are ſome things peculiar in your Religion which give Proteſtants juſt grounds of Jealouſie, and make your Caſe very different from that of other Parties who diſſent from the National Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The firſt</hi> is this, That you own a Dependence upon a Foreign Power, and a Power which is a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62728:8"/> declared Enemy to all Proteſtants. You own for the Vicar of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Head of your Church, a Perſon who pretends to a Power to Depoſe Princes, and to give away their Dominions to ſuch of your Church as are able to get them; and who in fact has very frequently Exerciſed this Power, and by it cauſed great Bloodſhed and Diſturbances in the World. Particularly, he has by Name Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated Two of our own Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. and Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth;</hi> and has forbid all their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to obey, or aſſiſt them, and has given away their Country to any Invader that would come and take it. And he does the ſame in effect, every Year in the famous <note n="*" place="margin">The form of all theſe Bulls may be ſeen in <hi>Bullar. Roman.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bulla Coenae</hi> by our King and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment at preſent.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:62728:8"/>
            <p>You cannot wonder if Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants are deſirous at leaſt to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arm all thoſe who own this Man for the Vicar of Jeſus Chriſt. And this in fact was the Cauſe of moſt of thoſe ſevere Laws which have been made againſt you. In the beginning of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s days the Papiſts gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally lived as eaſie and quiet as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Subjects; but when the Pope <hi>Excommunicated</hi> the Queen, and Prieſts were ſent from the Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries abroad to alienate the Hearts of Her Subjects, and Conſpiracies were entred into againſt her; then were thoſe ſevere Laws made as againſt thoſe that were Enemies to the State.</p>
            <p>It is very well known how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Conſpiracies followed that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication through the whole
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62728:9"/> courſe of her Reign, and what danger the Nation was in from the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Invaſion, which was undertaken upon the inſtigation of Romiſh Prieſts, and upon the Title which the Pope gave the King of <hi>Spain</hi> to the Kingdom of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I ſhall not inſiſt upon theſe things, or the many Provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions we have had ever ſince to this day; or the great danger we may be in at preſent; ſo far I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve muſt appear reaſonable to all indifferent Perſons, that it is fit for us to make all thoſe who expect to enjoy the Privileges of other Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to renounce an Authority ſo dangerous to us.</p>
            <p>It may, perhaps, be ſaid that there are ſome among you who do not own the Pope to have ſuch Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62728:9"/> and that therefore we may ſafely deal more gently with them.</p>
            <p>As to this, I ſhall not inſiſt at preſent to ſhew how far this Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Popes to Excommunicate and deprive Heretical Princes and States is a Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> this is certain, that it has been long pretended to by the Head of that Church; and thoſe who do not approve of it ought to ſpeak out, and to renounce Communion with him as a Tyrant and an Uſurper, and a Heretick by pretending ſuch Power from Jeſus Chriſt which was never giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en him: But ſo long as they ſtick by him, and own him for the Head of their Church, and the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car of Jeſus Chriſt, for the Judge of Controverſies, and the Supreme director of their Conſciences, they muſt not wonder if Proteſtants can
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62728:10"/> have no Confidence in them; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if we conſider how many Methods of Deceit have been taught and recommended by thoſe among them, who have been, and are ſtill the great Guides of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> 2d <hi>Conſideration</hi> I would propoſe is this, That Proteſtants have a Right by the Principle of Self-Preſervation to take ſuch Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods with thoſe of the Roman Communion, as may put it out of their power to do them a miſchief; <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. Concil. Lat. Can. 3. de Haereticis, which is called a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral council by that of <hi>Conſtans</hi> Seſſ. 19. and by that or <hi>Trent.</hi> Seſſ. 24.</note> becauſe Papiſts are obliged by the Laws of their Religion to perſecute Proteſtants; and theſe are Laws that have been as much put in Execution when e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it has been in their power,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62728:10"/> and it could be done with ſafety, as any Laws they have.</p>
            <p>It would be thought too in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidious to reckon up all the Wars and Maſſacres, Burnings and Crulties of all ſorts that have been and are ſtill in the World upon this account; eſpecially what has been done in a manner under our view in a Neighbour Country, the ſad effects of which not only our ſelves but all the Proteſtant Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries in <hi>Europe</hi> ſee and feel, by thoſe vaſt Numbers of poor Creatures that flock to us to preſerve their Conſciences and beg their Bread: Only thus far we cannot forbear to take Notice, that there have been more hard things ſuffered for not ſubmitting to the Pope than ever were inflicted upon Chriſtians for their Religion by all the Heathen Perſecutors together.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:62728:11"/>
            <p>Were theſe things the effects only of ſuddain Paſſion, or Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of State, which often do hard things to one another; there might be however ſome hope left that it might be otherwiſe, ſhould we ever again come into their power: But when Men are cruel upon a ſteddy ſettled Principle of Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, there is nothing left but to guard our ſelves againſt them as well as we can. Not that we may lawfully do hard things to them becauſe they have done ſo to us, or our Brethren; for that would be Revenge, or at beſt the imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a very bad Example: But eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man has by nature a Right to defend himſelf, and if that makes it wiſe or neceſſary for him to do ſome things which otherwiſe he has no Inclination to, it is not his fault, but the fault of thoſe who bring that neceſſity upon him.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:62728:11"/>
            <p>We are convinced that if Popery ſhould prevail in <hi>England,</hi> we ſhould not long enjoy our Eſtates, or perhaps Lives, if we would not comply with it; and we are ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that more than once we have been in great danger of this; ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially lately, when it was almoſt a Miracle that we were ſaved from it. We are ſenſible alſo that they are a reſtleſs uneaſie Party; that they have mighty dependencies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad which have much prevailed of late; that we can't tell what Foreign Power may be invited o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, or in ſucceeding times what incouragement they may have at home; and therefore we do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that meerly in our own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence we may juſtly take as effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al meaſures as we can to keep their Prieſts from among them, who we are ſatisfied have been and are
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62728:12"/> like to be <hi>Incendiaries;</hi> and to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert their <hi>Eſtates</hi> into better Hands of their own <hi>Relations,</hi> that they may not be turned againſt us. To conclude this matter; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding theſe Reaſons, we have to guard our ſelves againſt Popery, yet there are here no Cruelties of an <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> no <hi>Burning,</hi> no ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away <hi>of Life,</hi> no <hi>Dragooning;</hi> nay, the greateſt part, the Traders, and thoſe of the poorer ſort are ſcarce touched in this Act; and as for others on whom it is hardeſt, thoſe of Eſtates, yet there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing done of a ſudden and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediable; there's Time allowed for Conſideration, and Place left for Repentance and better Thoughts; and in the mean time their Perſons are ſecure, and they are at Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to go into any other Country with all the Money and Goods they can get, without danger of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62728:12"/> being ſent to the Gallies, if they are caught; which are Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges a great many poor Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures we have lately heard of would take to be very great Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſons to perſuade thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the grounds of their Religion.</note> As far as a private Man may venture to give his Opinion of the Actions of his Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors, theſe I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe (joyned with ſome peculiar Inſolencies at this time, very well known in the Kingdom) were the chief Reaſons the King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment went upon in making this and former Laws againſt you; and if our Religion be true and yours falſe, I believe you your ſelves will hardly condemn us for it. And this is the <hi>next thing</hi> I would deſire you to conſider of; that you would not take it for granted,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62728:13"/> that you are in the right, and ſo call this Perſecution for Conſcience ſake, but that you would take this Opportunity to examin the grounds of your Religion; which will be an advantage to you which way ſo ever the matter end.</p>
            <p>If upon Examination you find your ſelves to have been in the wrong, you will then have the Benefit and Comfort of being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted from very dangerous Errors and Practices, and of living quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and preſerving your Eſtates to your Families; but if otherwiſe, you find reaſon for your preſent Opinions, it will be a mighty com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to you in whatever you ſuffer, that you do it upon evidence and conviction of Conſcience; and not upon Fancy and Prejudice from your Education.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:62728:13"/>
            <p>And ſo much, I think, in Juſtice you owe to your Children, not to Breed them up in a Religion which muſt deprive them of their Eſtates, till you have well examined the Truth of it your ſelves: It will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed be the greateſt Bleſſing to them to Breed them up in the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion let the conſequences as to this World be what they will; but at leaſt, Matters ought to be well weighed before you do what will be on all accounts ſo great an Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to them, if your Religion ſhould prove falſe, which perhaps, I may give you juſt reaſon to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect before I conclude this Paper, if you will but read it without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice and partiality. Only one thing I would deſire you to have a care of, that you be not too nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſenſible of the <hi>diſhonour</hi> of changing your Opinion, now it
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62728:14"/> may ſeem to be for your Intereſt. This I know is a Conſideration apt to work very ſtrong, and to give a greater Biaſs to the Minds of ſome Perſons than the greateſt Intereſt in the World. But a good Chriſtian ſhould be contented with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to go <hi>through evil report and good report,</hi> and ſhould deſpiſe the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the World, ſo he can but pleaſe God and ſave his Soul.</p>
            <p>And this ſuggeſts <hi>another Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration,</hi> that not only your Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in this World, but your Souls are very much concerned in this Examination. Your Church is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed by Proteſtants as guilty of a great number of dangerous Errors, and of very ſinful Practices; of Superſtition and Idolatry, of being the Authors, and conſequently having the guilt of a great Schiſm in the Church; and it concerns you
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62728:14"/> to conſider whether this Charge be true, or no? Whatever Charity Proteſtants may have for thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, who have no means of being better Informed, they have juſt reaſon to look upon ſuch Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and ſinful Practices as like to be fatal to thoſe among you who might be better informed and will not.</p>
            <p>But there is <hi>another Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which perhaps may weigh more with you in this Matter than the Opinion of Proteſtants; which is, That if this Charge againſt you be true; if you are guilty of Schiſm and Idolatry, and ſuch groſs Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, by the Opinion of your own Divines, you cannot be Saved. This is a Matter that they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves often urge againſt that Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which Proteſtants are apt to have for ſincere honeſt People a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62728:15"/> you that are invincibly Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant; beſides, the very ſame Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which they urge to ſhew the danger that we are in, do equally hold againſt you, ſuppoſing that you are in the wrong. If it be <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy</hi> in us to deny the Articles of your <hi>new Creed,</hi> ſuppoſing they are true, it muſt be <hi>Hereſy</hi> in you to believe them, ſuppoſing they are falſe; the Reaſon is the ſame in both; and ſo as to the <hi>Schiſm,</hi> if your pretended Head of the Church be guilty of Tyranny, and Uſurpation, and Hereſy and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, and of impoſing theſe upon Chriſtians, it is He and his Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are in the <hi>Schiſm,</hi> and not We. And then, all thoſe dreadful things which your own Writers ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Schiſm and Hereſy, do as much belong to you, ſuppoſing you are in the wrong; as they do to us if we are ſo. And therefore
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62728:15"/> if what they ſay, have any weight with you, it ought to make you conſider ſeriouſly whether you are in the right, or no.</p>
            <p>I the rather urge this, becauſe it contains a full Anſwer to that piece of Sophiſtry wherewith you often deceive your ſelves, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to delude us; <hi>That you are ſafe by the confeſſion of all Sides, but we are not, and that therefore we ought in prudence to come over unto you.</hi> Which is falſe; for by your own Opinion you are not ſafe, but in a Damnable Condition, ſuppoſing that you are in the wrong: There is no difference at all betwixt us and you in this Matter, except on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly where the Truth lies. For if our charitable Opinion of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God to invincible Ignorance be true, this is Comfort to us, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing we are miſtaken, as it is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62728:16"/> to you ſuppoſing you are ſo; and on the other ſide, if your Damning Doctrine be true, this is as dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to you as it is to us.</p>
            <p>It lies therefore upon you even from the Opinion of your own Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines to be very impartial in exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining the Grounds of your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; tho' indeed our Obligation to ſearch after Truth does not ariſe chiefly from the danger of being miſtaken, but from that deſire that every good Man ſhould have to pleaſe God, and to ſerve him as well as he can; and the want of this deſire has more danger and malignity in it than a great many miſtakes in Matters of meer Belief. To be only concerned to avoid thoſe Errors that may Damn us, is the ſame undutiful Temper toward God, as it would be in a Son to have no concern to pleaſe his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62728:16"/> but only ſo far as that he may not be diſ-inherited. Many Errors that may not be fatal to Ignorant People, may yet be very diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to God, bring a great Scandal to our Holy Religion, and do a great deal of miſchief in the World; and theſe are things which a good Chriſtian would have a great care of, tho' at the ſame time he might hope that God would pardon him, ſhould he ignorantly fall into them.</p>
            <p>This, I hope, may be ſufficient to convince you, that you ought to examine well the Grounds you go upon in your Religion. I ſhall now endeavour to ſhew you ſome of the Errors which we charge up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Church, and the Reaſons why we Renounced them, and why we think it your Duty to do ſo too.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:62728:17"/>
            <p>As to the particulars, I ſhall chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confine my ſelf to thoſe which the <hi>preſent Act</hi> mentions, thoſe to be renounced in the <hi>Teſt,</hi> and in the <hi>Oath of Supremacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before I proceed to them, I would ſpeak a little to that which is the great ground and ſupport of all your other Errors, the <hi>Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of your Church;</hi> which if I can ſhew you to be a meer pretence without any Warrant or Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from Jeſus Chriſt, you will then more eaſily hearken to what can be ſaid in the other Matters.</p>
            <p>It cannot be expected that I ſhould handle theſe Controverſies in their full extent in the ſhort compaſs which it's fit this preſent Addreſs ſhould have; but if you find what is ſaid here to have
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62728:17"/> weight in it, and that it gives you juſt cauſe of doubting, I hope you will be ſo kind to your ſelves as to come to ſome of our Divines who may inform you more fully, or to read ſome of thoſe Books which have at large examined theſe Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">About the Infalibility of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Infallibility</hi> is the thing in the World which a good Chriſtian ſhould have the leaſt prejudice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt; for tho' I do now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, ſince I ſee plainly that God has appointed no <hi>Infalliable Judge,</hi> that it is beſt all things conſidered that there ſhould be none: Yet I muſt confeſs, were I to judge of things by my own Reaſon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any regard to what God has done, I ſhould be apt to think ſuch a Judge would be a great Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62728:18"/> to the World. I could not but be very glad to find an Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble way to end Diſputes among Chriſtians; but Chriſtianity has now been in the World near 1700 Years, and I do not know any Age in which there have not been great Conteſts and Diſputes, except ſome few that were ſo ſtupidly Ignorant that Men hardly knew any thing of Religion, and then no wonder if there were not many Diſputes; from whence, I cannot but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that either it is the Will of God for wiſe Reaſons, that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies ſhould not be ended; or that an Infallible Judge cannot end them, or that there has all this while been no Infallible Judge.</p>
            <p>But to conſider this Matter more methodically; I have theſe <hi>Two,</hi> I think, ſtrong <hi>Reaſons,</hi> which make me conclude, there is no ſuch Judge.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:62728:18"/>
            <list>
               <item>I. That you your ſelves are not agreed who he is. And</item>
               <item>II. That the Reaſons commonly brought to prove that there is, or ought to be ſuch a one, do, if well weighed, rather prove againſt it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. That you your ſelves are not agreed who he is, and this is a mighty prejudice in a thing of this Conſequence; certainly that which it appointed by God to end all Controverſies, ought to be a thing out of Controverſy it ſelf. There ought to be a plain Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, a plain Deſignation of the Perſon, or Perſons, that Chriſtians might know where to repair in their Difficulties. But is this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter plain? Can you aſſign us any Man, or number of Men, that have, I won't ſay ſuch a Commiſſion,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62728:19"/> but that in fact only have ever ſince the Apoſtles Days been repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to by Chriſtians, and looked upon as their Judge, and their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations thought to be Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? If you can, I for my part ſhall very thankfully ſubmit, and own the Authority. But let us ſee what the People of your own Church ſay about it. You are ſure that you have <hi>Infallibility,</hi> but you don't know where it is. Some ſay it is in the <hi>Pope,</hi> as Head of the Church, and Vicar of Jeſus Chriſt; others ſay, it is in a <hi>General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil,</hi> but theſe differs. Some ſay, they are Infallible if Confirmed by the Pope; others, that their Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations do not need his <hi>Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> But beſides theſe, there are others that ſay it is (they don't know how) in the <hi>diffuſive Body of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:62728:19"/>
            <p>Now pray <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> does this ſound like the Voice of Truth, or a Method appointed by God to end all <hi>Controverſies?</hi> In Matters of ſmaller moment we allow Men to abound in their own Senſe, and to differ from one another; at leaſt we cannot conclude they are all in the wrong becauſe they differ; but in this we may, and ought, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if there were any ſuch thing as Infallibility in the Church, and that deſigned to be the Guide of all Chriſtians, it could not be a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, or matter of Controverſie where it was lodged; we ſhould ſee the plain Appointment of God, or at leaſt we ſhould ſee in the Hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory of the Church to whom Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians had appeal'd in all Ages. And for the Chriſtian Church to be at uncertainty where to go for ſo long a time to end their Diſputes; is the ſame ſort of Abſurdity that it
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62728:20"/> would be in a Nation for 1700 Years together not to know where to go for <hi>Juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this Abſurdity will appear the greater if <hi>we conſider</hi> beſides this, that tho' the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> be united together in a ſtrong Bond of External Government and Polity, yet in truth and reality this Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence about the Guide of their Faith makes them <hi>different Churches</hi> and of <hi>different Religions.</hi> For a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Guide and Judge, if he be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem'd Infallible, muſt make a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent <hi>Rule of Faith;</hi> becauſe his Determinations muſt be part of the Rule of Faith; and a different Rule of Faith muſt make a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Religion. To inſtance in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, thoſe that own <hi>General Councils</hi> to be Infallible, muſt take their Decrees as part of the <hi>Rule</hi> of their <hi>Faith;</hi> but now they that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62728:20"/> own the <hi>Pope</hi> for Infallible, muſt beſides, take in all his ſolemn <hi>Determinations,</hi> and ſo have a much larger <hi>Rule</hi> of their <hi>Faith</hi> than the other, and in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Caſes, very different, and what may be much more different than it is now; for if he be indeed Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible, as many of them ſay that he is, he may determine <hi>Vice</hi> to be <hi>Vertue,</hi> and <hi>Vertue</hi> to be <hi>Vice,</hi> he may fall into great Errors, as other Fallible Men may do, and as ſome of them in fact have done; and yet thoſe of that Church who own him to be Infallible, muſt take theſe things as part of the Rule of their Faith, and Manners.</p>
            <p>Theſe I take to be undeniable Conſequences from the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences among them about their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Judge; and I think, from all together, I may well inferr, that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62728:21"/> there is no ſuch thing; ſince it ſo much concerns the World, if there be any, to be at a certainty about it; and yet the greateſt part of Chriſtians know nothing at all of the Matter; and thoſe who do pretend to know it are, in truth, as much at a loſs about it as thoſe that do not; only they agree in a Name, which leads them different ways, perhaps all wrong, and only more <hi>Infallibly</hi> ſecures them in Error.</p>
            <p>But I would now ſpeak a word or two to the <hi>ſeveral Pretences</hi> to it. The <hi>firſt Pretender</hi> is the <hi>Pope,</hi> who ſeems indeed to have the beſt Pretence; for if God do think ſit to appoint ſuch a one, a ſingle Perſon who is always ready to hear and determine Matters, ſeems moſt proper, at leaſt much more proper than a number of Men to be ſent from all Parts of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62728:21"/> the World, who can ſeldom meet, and never without a great deal of trouble; and this ſeems to be the moſt genuine Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> which makes the Pope the <hi>Center of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> makes Communion with him ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and a Mark of a <hi>True Church,</hi> and makes his Church the <hi>Mother</hi> and <hi>Miſtreſs</hi> of all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; which is hardly Senſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Infallibility, But as to his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, I ſhall conſider it preſently, when I come to examine his <hi>Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy,</hi> for if that fall, his Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility muſt fall along with it. One thing only I would obſerve here, That it ſeems apparent from hence that the Primitive Church knew nothing of his Infallibility, in that they took to that troubleſome and chargeable and tedious way of end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Diſputes by <hi>Councils;</hi> which, ſuppoſing he be appointed
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62728:22"/> by God to determine them, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to do it infallibly, were not only uſeleſs and impertinent, but indeed dangerous, and very apt to turn Men from the way by which God had appointed the Church to be Guided. A number of Men may be good for Counſel and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of one that is Fallible, but muſt be utterly unneceſſary and an incumbrance to one that is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible. And therefore ſince the <hi>Church</hi> has always made uſe of <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils</hi> either <hi>General</hi> or <hi>Provincial,</hi> to determine Matters of <hi>Faith,</hi> I may certainly conclude they knew nothing of his <hi>Infallibility.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of General Councils.</note> As to <hi>General Councils,</hi> it is not our preſent Buſineſs to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of what <hi>uſe</hi> they may be to the Church, or what <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal deference</hi> is due to them if
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62728:22"/> we could have thoſe that are truly <hi>General;</hi> but whether they are <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible</hi> or not? Now as to this, I would only propoſe this <hi>one ſhort Conſideration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That they are not of the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun 300 Years after <hi>Chriſt</hi> by <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine;</hi> now whatever Wiſdom there may have been in calling ſo many Biſhops together to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour by their <hi>Authority</hi> to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Differences of the <hi>Church,</hi> or to Eſtabliſh good Diſcipline, yet it was ſtill a Humane Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and I know no way to annex <hi>Infallibility</hi> to what is ſo. If 3 or 400 Men meet together, each of which is confeſſedly <hi>Fallible,</hi> they muſt altogether be ſo, unleſs you can ſhew a Promiſe from <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> to ſecure them from <hi>Error:</hi> Now if there be ſuch a Promiſe as
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62728:23"/> this, we <hi>Proteſtants</hi> expect to find it in <hi>Scripture;</hi> but however, <hi>you your ſelves</hi> cannot pretend to it unleſs it be in <hi>Scripture,</hi> or comes down to you by <hi>Tradition</hi> from <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> As to <hi>Scripture</hi> the very Name and Thing of <hi>a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Council</hi> is quite unknown to it; and as for <hi>Tradition,</hi> that could as little convey down any ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, for the whole Thing was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known in the <hi>Church</hi> for 300 Years, not ſo much as the Name ever heard of.</p>
            <p>As for the Meeting at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> of which we have an account in the 15 of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> it was only a Meeting of thoſe that were then at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> upon occaſion of a Complaint that was brought to them; And it was a Meeting of Men, moſt of which were by immediate Inſpiration ſingly <hi>Infallible;</hi> and therefore
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62728:23"/> can be no <hi>Preſident</hi> for a Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Biſhops</hi> from all Parts of the World: And much leſs does this which was an accidental Meeting, contein an <hi>Inſtitution</hi> for the future, and a Promiſe to make them <hi>Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible</hi> when met in a Body together, who ſingly are but like other Men.</p>
            <p>If it be ſaid, that they muſt be <hi>Infallible</hi> becauſe they repreſent the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church</hi> which is <hi>Infallible;</hi> the Difficulty will ſtill return; for tho' we ſhould grant the <hi>Church</hi> to be <hi>Infallible,</hi> yet who appointed this <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations?</hi> did <hi>Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> Has he annexed a Promiſe of <hi>Infallibility</hi> to it? Without ſuch a Promiſe as this, there may be <hi>Infallibility</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> and yet 3 or 400 <hi>Biſhops,</hi> or the Majority of them may be miſtaken, they may be a Number
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62728:24"/> of Men packed together to ſerve a <hi>Turn,</hi> they may be guided by Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction or Intereſt, by their own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, or the Intereſt of thoſe who ſend them, as in fact it has been more than once; or if they are good Men, that will not make them <hi>Infallible.</hi> We may contrive as wiſely as we pleaſe, but we can never be certain to annex the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural Aſſiſtance of God to our own Schemes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To conclude this Head,</hi> If the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility you</hi> boaſt of be fixed in <hi>General Councils,</hi> there was none in the <hi>Church</hi> for 300 Years, when yet there was the moſt need of them, there having been a greater number of dangerous <hi>Hereſies</hi> in that Time, than have been in the <hi>Church</hi> ever ſince. But what is worſe, either there was no true <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> all that while,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62728:24"/> or elſe it muſt be granted, that we may have it without an <hi>Infallible Guide; Chriſtians</hi> were then, at leaſt in this reſpect, in the ſame Condition that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are now; And I hope it will be granted, that we need not deſire to be in a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than they were.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Laſt</hi> refuge for <hi>Infallibility,</hi> is, that it is in the <hi>diffuſive Body of the Church.</hi> But this I believe muſt be at laſt reduced to one or other of the former; for it will be very difficult to ſhew how the <hi>Church</hi> can exert it's <hi>Infallibility</hi> ſo as to be a Guide, but either by means of it's <hi>Head</hi> which you make the <hi>Pope,</hi> or elſe by the way of a <hi>General Council;</hi> there is no other way whereby thoſe of <hi>your Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> can be certain what is the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> and what are the <hi>Traditions</hi> of <hi>your Church</hi> but one of theſe,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:62728:25"/> and therefore having conſidered both of them already, I ſhall proceed to conſider the way of Reaſoning <hi>your Divines</hi> commonly make uſe of to prove that there either is, or ought to be ſuch an <hi>Infallible Judge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for what they ſay from <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> it is commonly urged ſo cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and with ſo much diffidence, that we may ſee they do not lay any great ſtreſs upon it: But that you may not be amuſed only with ſome general Words in truth nothing to the purpoſe, I deſire you would conſider, that there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no <hi>Infallibility</hi> which can ſerve to be <hi>your Guide</hi> but only that of the <hi>Pope,</hi> or a <hi>General Council,</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from <hi>Scripture</hi> can be perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, but that which proves either the one or the other. No Man, or Number of Men can be <hi>Infallible</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:62728:25"/> without a particular Aſſiſtance, and we cannot be ſure <hi>they</hi> are ſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a particular Promiſe. And therefore when you hear any thing alledged from <hi>Scripture,</hi> only ask <hi>your ſelves</hi> What does this prove? Does it prove the <hi>Pope</hi> to be <hi>Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible?</hi> Or does it prove <hi>a General Council</hi> to be ſo? If it do not prove one of them, it proves nothing in this Matter, for you are never the nearer <hi>your Guide</hi> for any thing elſe.</p>
            <p>Now as to <hi>General Councils,</hi> I have ſhewed already, that there is not the leaſt hint of them in <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> and as for the Title of the <hi>Pope</hi> to it, I ſhall conſider it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently in examining his <hi>Supremacy:</hi> And in the mean time ſhall take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice a little what they urge from <hi>Reaſon</hi> to prove that there ought to be ſuch a <hi>Judge;</hi> ought to be
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62728:26"/> I ſay, for all the <hi>Reaſon</hi> in the World without a <hi>Revelation</hi> from God can never prove that there is one, it being a thing that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends meerly upon the appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and good-pleaſure of God.</p>
            <p>The Writers of the <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi> it muſt be confeſſed, talk Plauſibly enough when they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the weakneſs of Human under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and the Infirmities of Human Nature; and I muſt ſay that in reading of them I could hardly forbear at leaſt to wiſh, that if it had pleaſed God, ſome effectual Remedy had been provided to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure Men from Error. But this did not at all influence me to think that God had done ſo, and that upon theſe Three Accounts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe we ſee in fact, that neither Mankind in general, nor
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62728:26"/> Chriſtians in particular have been ſecured from Errors; that there have been as many Conteſts and Differences among Chriſtians as we can ſuppoſe there would have been, taking it for granted that they were left in the State, we ſay they were, without any <hi>Infallible Guide</hi> to direct them; and therefore whatever force ſuch a Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the neceſſity of ending Controverſies might have had in the firſt Times of our Religion; the matter of Fact does now in a great meaſure take it off; becauſe in 1700 Years the <hi>Church</hi> has not been freed from them. From whence, as I ſaid before, we may inferr, either that it is not the Will of God that Controverſies ſhould be ended, or that an <hi>Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Judge</hi> will not end them, or that there is no <hi>Infallible Judge;</hi> either of which, takes away the force of this Argument.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:62728:27"/>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe this whole way of Arguing from the weakneſs of our Underſtanding, and proneſs to Error, and the like, proves no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in particular, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently does not bring us at all nearer Satisfaction than we were before. The moſt natural <hi>Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> from it is, That every Man is to be of the Religion of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; for that makes through work, and excuſes us from uſing our Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Reaſon at all in the Matter; whereas in <hi>your Way,</hi> however you may cry out of the uncertainty of our own Reaſon, yet you muſt uſe it in a great many material Points, and indeed, found all the certainty <hi>you</hi> have upon it; <hi>you</hi> muſt for inſtance, Judge by your own Reaſon, whether the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion</hi> be true, or not; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther among all the Profeſſors of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62728:27"/> Chriſtianity, <hi>yours</hi> be the <hi>True Church;</hi> whether there be any <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Judge</hi> or no, and who he is, and what his Determinations are. Theſe are things of great weight, and of a great latitude, and indeed take in the chief Points of Religion, and yet theſe things muſt be judged of by that Reaſon which God has given every Man, or they cannot be judged of at all; whereas <hi>your</hi> whole way of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the fallibility of our Underſtanding, either proves that we cannot judge with certainty of theſe Matters, or it proves no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This whole way of talking is to me a ſtrong prejudice againſt what you would prove by it. For if you had a plain Inſtitution or a Promiſe of ſuch a Judg to ſhew, there would be no need of this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:62728:28"/> that would be Sufficient; and without that, no Man can be <hi>Infallible;</hi> and we may be ſure that Men have no ſuch Commiſſion or Promiſe to ſhew, when they are forced to uſe ſo much Cavilling and Diſpute about the matter, which is indeed nothing to the purpoſe without the other.</p>
            <p>We do with much more reaſon inferr, that ſince God has not thought fit to give any ſuch <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,</hi> that therefore we muſt make the beſt of thoſe other means which he is pleaſed to allow us; to <hi>ſearch the Scriptures,</hi> and endeavour to underſtand them as well as we can. And this is the Method that our <hi>Saviour</hi> directed, <hi>Search the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, for in them ye think ye have E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life, and they teſtifie of me.</hi> From which Words, we may plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly infer theſe following things.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:62728:28"/>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Jews</hi> had at that time no <hi>Infallible Guide</hi> in Matters of Religion; for if they had our Saviour would have directed them thither, but we ſee he directs them to the <hi>Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. We may inferr that the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons our Saviour ſpoke to, had without an <hi>Infallible Guide</hi> ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Abilities to underſtand the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and to have true <hi>Faith;</hi> otherwiſe we may be ſure he would not have ſent them thither, and if they could underſtand the <hi>Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament</hi> without ſuch a Guide, much more may Chriſtians under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the <hi>New</hi> which is much eaſier.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We may inferr that Private Perſons, (for ſuch our Saviour ſpoke to,) may have ſufficient aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62728:29"/> of <hi>Divine Truths</hi> from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> tho' they go againſt the Governors of the <hi>Church;</hi> for our Saviour tells them, that they might find in the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> that he was the True <hi>Meſſias,</hi> tho' the <hi>Chief Prieſts</hi> did at that time reject him, and were afterwards the Authors of his Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixion: All which do abſolutely overthrow the neceſſity of an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Judge</hi> in order to <hi>True Faith.</hi> And there cannot be one thing ſaid againſt <hi>Protestants</hi> examining the <hi>Scriptures</hi> now; but what would have held as well, againſt the Command of our Saviour here to the <hi>Jews;</hi> unleſs they can ſhew us a poſitive Inſtitution of an <hi>Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Guide;</hi> but all the Arguments from Reaſon, and the imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Underſtanding are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly the ſame in both Caſes.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:62728:29"/>
            <p>The truth is, all our Saviour's Preaching did ſuppoſe this, for it had been a vain thing to Preach to People who had not abilities to underſtand: And if we go further, to the Preaching of the Apoſtles, we ſhall find that they endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to prove the truth of what they ſaid out of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> by which they appealed to the Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Hearers, and made them proper Judges of what they ſaid, as far as their own Salvation was concerned in it. We ſee in <hi>Acts</hi> 17.11. The <hi>Bereans</hi> were commended as more <hi>noble than thoſe of Theſſalonica, becauſe they ſearched the Scriptures daily to ſee whether the things the Apoſtles prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched were ſo, or not.</hi> The Apoſtle St. <hi>John</hi> commands Chriſtians <hi>to try the Spirits;</hi> that is, to examine the pretences that any ſhould make to the Spirit of God, which ſuppoſes
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:62728:30"/> that their Underſtanding, how fallible ſoever, was ſufficient to judge in theſe Matters.</p>
            <p>In a word, the Writers and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſaries of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> do themſelves, when they don't think of it, in effect confeſs this; for when they bring <hi>Scripture,</hi> and other Arguments to perſuade us to come over to <hi>their Church,</hi> I would ask them, are we proper Judges of theſe things, or are we not? Will our Faith be a true Faith, that is founded upon theſe <hi>Scriptures,</hi> or theſe Reaſons that you here bring? If it be ſo, then we may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand for our ſelves, and there is no neceſſity in order to true Faith, of an <hi>Infallible Judge;</hi> but if it be not ſo, there ought to be then an end of Diſputes; for it's in vain to Diſpute where it's ſuppoſed that we cannot underſtand or judge, and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:62728:30"/> all offering of <hi>Scripture</hi> or <hi>Reaſon</hi> to prove the truth of their Opinions is only affront and mockery.</p>
            <p>But it may be it will be ſaid, Don't we ſee People differ about the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of <hi>Scripture?</hi> ſome go one way and ſome another, and yet all are conſident of their own; how can we be ſure that we are in the right any more than they who are as confident in what they ſay as we are?</p>
            <p>Now this Objection is founded upon this, that we cannot have certainty of what is once Diſputed; which is contrary to the Common Opinion of Mankind, who would have done Diſputing, if they thought they could not be certain when once Men differed from them. This does indeed overthrow all Reaſon and Religion. Some have
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:62728:31"/> ventured to Diſpute the <hi>Being</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and many more the <hi>Truth</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> and yet I hope we may be very certain of the Truth of both theſe. But I would only urge at preſent this <hi>one Conſideration.</hi> Are all the World a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed about their <hi>Infallible Judge?</hi> If not, how can they be certain of that? But to preſs this Matter a little more plainly; they ſay for inſtance, that we can't from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be certain of the Divinity of our Saviour, becauſe the <hi>Socinian's</hi> a ſmall number of Men, diſpute that Matter. But the ſame <hi>Socinians</hi> deny their <hi>Infallible Judge,</hi> and therefore that muſt at leaſt be as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain as the other: And not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Socinians,</hi> but all <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> deny it, which muſt make it ſtill more uncertain; and not only all the <hi>Protestants,</hi> but the <hi>Greek, Armenian, Aethiopian</hi> Churches, a
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:62728:31"/> vaſt Body of Men, which muſt ſtill add to the uncertainty; and not only all theſe, but all that in any Age or Nation have ever differed from the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> for whoever differs from them muſt deny their <hi>Infallibility;</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently this muſt have been Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted not only as much as any one Point, but as much as all the reſt together.</p>
            <p>This, I think, is a demonſtrative Anſwer to this whole way of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing, and ſhews the manifeſt Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity of it; for it makes things uncertain becauſe they are Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and yet makes the moſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted thing in all the World the Foundation of all the certainty they have.</p>
            <p>I have been the longer in examin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Point of the <hi>Infallibility</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:62728:32"/> of your Church, as being that which is the great ſupport of all your other Errors.</p>
            <p>I now proceed to ſpeak ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the particulars I promiſed; and firſt I ſhall begin with <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation,</hi> which is the firſt thing Renounced in the <hi>Teſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Senſe of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in this Matter ſeems to be this, That tho' Believers in the faithful and due receiving of this Holy Sacrament are made Partakers of the <hi>Benefits</hi> of the Death of <hi>Christ,</hi> that is, of the breaking of his Body and the ſhedding his Blood, and ſo may be properly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough ſaid to be partakers of his Body and Blood, yet that which they take into their Mouths is real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but Bread and Wine; but Bread and Wine ſet apart for a holy Uſe,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:62728:32"/> to repreſent the breaking of the Body and the ſhedding of the Blood of our Bleſſed Saviour; and therefore in a <hi>Sacramental ſenſe</hi> may be called his Body and Blood, tho' in <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>reality</hi> they are but Bread and Wine.</p>
            <p>Both Sides do in ſome Senſe own a <hi>real Preſence</hi> of Chriſt in this Sacrament, but this one thing, if obſerved, will ſufficiently ſhew the difference; That <hi>Protestants</hi> ſay, that in the devout and holy Uſe of this Sacrament, Chriſt will be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with his Grace and Aſſiſtance to the Souls of good People; but that the Things which appear before us, which we eat and drink, are not Chriſt, but Bread and Wine.</p>
            <p>Thoſe of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> on the other ſide, ſay, That the Thing which lies before them,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:62728:33"/> which they put into their Mouths, tho' before <hi>Conſecration</hi> they are Bread and Wine, yet upon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing thoſe Words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> and <hi>this is my Blood,</hi> they loſe their own <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Subſtance</hi> of <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> and become <hi>very Chriſt,</hi> the very ſame Chriſt that was Born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and that ſuffered upon the Croſs. And therefore pay them the ſame Divine Honour and Worſhip as if God or Chriſt did truly and openly appear before them.</p>
            <p>Now the whole ground of this Diſpute lies in the Words of the <hi>Inſtitution, This is my Body,</hi> and <hi>this is my Blood. They</hi> ſay, that the Words ought to be underſtood in the plain literal Senſe; <hi>we</hi> ſay they ought to be underſtood as uſed by Chriſt in his Inſtituting a <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> that is, appointing one thing
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:62728:33"/> to be a <hi>repreſentation</hi> and a <hi>memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> of another; and which becauſe it does repreſent, may very well be called by the Name of that Thing which is repreſented by it, which we think to be a very natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, eaſy way of ſpeaking, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable as to that preſent occaſion, ſo to other terms of Speech of the ſame nature which had been in uſe among thoſe People to whom our Saviour ſpoke.</p>
            <p>But in particular, the time in which our Saviour Inſtituted this Sacrament was when they had been eating the <hi>Paſſover;</hi> which was a Feaſt much of the ſame Nature a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Jews</hi> that this is among <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> that was appointed by God in memory of thier Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance when the Angel of God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the <hi>Firſt-born</hi> of all the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and this in memory of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:62728:34"/> that much greater Bleſſing to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians by the Death and Sufferings of Jeſus Chriſt. As therefore the Maſter of the Family when he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed the <hi>Paſchal Lamb,</hi> was to ſay, <hi>This is the Lord's Paſſover,</hi> as being Inſtituted in memory of the Lord's <hi>paſſing over</hi> the Houſes of the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> ſo now being to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute a new Sacrament for his Church of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as that was for the <hi>Jews,</hi> he appoints a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial of the breaking of his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and the ſhedding of his Blood, and in the very ſame figure of Speech that the other was. <hi>This is my Body,</hi> or this is <hi>the Lord's Body,</hi> could be no ſtrange form of Speech to them, who juſt before had heard him ſay, <hi>This is the Lord's Paſſever,</hi> and who had been conſtantly uſed to that form of Speech. And accordingly, we do not find that they were in any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:62728:34"/> or ſurprize in the Matter, which they could not have avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed if the Words are to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood juſt as they ſound; for it was a Matter more than a little a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazing, eſpecially to thoſe who never had been uſed to ſuch ſort of Myſteries, that their Maſter ſhould take a piece of Bread in his Hand, and with ſpeaking a few Words, ſhould make it become, without any apparent change, that very Body which was then ſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them. That he ſhould hold his own Body whole and entire in his own Hand; that they ſhould put the ſame <hi>one</hi> Body whole and entire into each of their Mouths, that they ſhould <hi>eat</hi> him firſt, and <hi>drink</hi> him afterwards, and yet that he ſhould ſtand by them <hi>untouched</hi> all the while; beſides the very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couthneſs and horror of the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, to eat their Maſter, a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:62728:35"/> whom they loved, and had reaſon to love, and to drink Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Blood; theſe are things one would think, ſhould at leaſt, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize them a little, and make them ask ſome Queſtions about it; for they are indeed ſtrange, monſtrous Abſurdities; whereas the ſenſe we give to the Words is natural and eaſy, eſpecially to the Perſons to whom they were ſpoken, as being uſed to ſuch expreſſions, and who had heard the like but juſt before, in a like Caſe.</p>
            <p>I have this one thing more to add in this Matter, That as the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Sacraments were <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Repreſentations</hi> as well as ours, and ſo were commonly called by the Name of what they repreſented; ſo the inward Bleſſings conveyed to them was the ſame that is convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Chriſtian Sacraments; and therefore the Apoſtle tells us, they
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:62728:35"/> 
               <hi>did all eat of the ſame ſpiritual meat, and drank of the ſame ſpiritual drink, for they drank of that ſpiritual Rock that followed them, and that Rock was Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.3,4.</note> Now here is altogether as plain evidence that the <hi>Jews</hi> did eat and drink Chriſt before he was Born as the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> do ſince: But that is a way of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> which thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> don't yet acknowledge; and we may conclude, that if the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle had known any thing of that Doctrine among Chriſtians he would have been more wary in his Expreſſions, and not have weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the credit of it by uſing the ſame ſort of Words where nothing of the ſame thing was meant.</p>
            <p>From hence we may give an account of that large Diſcourſe of our Saviour in the Sixth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:62728:36"/> of St. <hi>John, My Fleſh is Meat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and my blood is drink indeed,</hi> &amp;c. For if he were Meat and Drink to the <hi>Jews</hi> ſo long before he was born, he might in the ſame manner be Meat and Drink to them ſtill without the porten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous way of putting his Body into their Mouths.</p>
            <p>Chriſt is ſaid to be a <hi>Lamb ſlain from the Foundation of the World;</hi> and in the ſame ſenſe was Meat and Drink to all good People from the Foundation of the World; that is, the benefits of his Death reach backward even to the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the World though he were put to death ſeveral Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Years after. And they are the Benefits of his Death which are the great <hi>Food of Souls,</hi> that which gives, and preſerves Life in them, as the Life of the Body
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:62728:36"/> is kept up by Meat and Drink.</p>
            <p>And this ſuggeſts <hi>another Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration,</hi> That we may know what ſort of eating this is, if we only conſider what ſort of <hi>Life</hi> is kept up by it. The eating and drinking of a <hi>Body</hi> is proper to keep up the <hi>Life</hi> of a <hi>Body,</hi> but it's only the inward Grace and Aſſiſtance of God that keeps up the <hi>Life</hi> of a <hi>Soul;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we then eat and drink for that, when we do by Faith or any other method take in that Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual nouriſhment.</p>
            <p>In a Word, Our Saviour ſays, <hi>He gave his fleſh for the life of the World,</hi> and we may then not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly be ſaid to eat his Fleſh, when we receive in that Spiritual Life and Nouriſhment procured by it. And that this is the Senſe is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:62728:37"/> from ſeveral expreſſions in that Diſcourſe, as in <hi>v.</hi> 35. <hi>And Jeſus ſaith unto them I am the Bread of Life, he that cometh to me ſhall never hunger, and he that believeth in me ſhall never thirſt;</hi> in which words there are Two things which directly contradict this groſs ſenſe of eating his very Body; Firſt that he alters here the expreſſion of Eating, and ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains himſelf, <hi>whoſoever comes to me, and whoſoever believes in me,</hi> which ſhews that this Bleſſing comes by <hi>Believing</hi> in Chriſt and not by groſs carnal <hi>Eating.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, The Bleſſing it ſelf is ſuch as does not belong to all that only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally receive the Sacrament but to ſuch only as come to Chriſt with true Faith; as may be ſeen not only in this Verſe but every where through that Diſcourſe; thus <hi>v.</hi> 51. <hi>If any man eat of this
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:62728:37"/> bread he ſhall live for ever.</hi> And <hi>v.</hi> 53. 54. <hi>Verily I ſay unto you, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ye eat the Fleſh of he Son of Man and drink his Blood ye have no life in you, whoſoever eateth my Fleſh and drinketh my Blood hath eternal life, and I will raiſe him up at the laſt day.</hi> Which words are very true if underſtood of the feeding our Souls by the Benefits received from the Body and Blood of Chriſt; but cannot be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of external eating of him in the Sacrament; for very wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men often do that according to the Opinion of the <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi> and are only the worſe inſtead of being the better for it.</p>
            <p>This I believe is abundantly ſufficient to ſhew that the Senſe we put upon the Sacramental words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> &amp;c. is natural and eaſie, agreeable to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:62728:38"/> the deſign of a Sacrament, and other expreſſions of the ſame kind in Scripture; and if it be ſo, we need not be ſolicitous to prove any thing more about it; for there are ſo many Abſurdities and groſs Contradictions in the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Opinion that we ought to lay hold of any thing that can but make ſenſe of the Words, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void thoſe Monſtrous Abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall now indeavour to prove from the Words them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that the ſenſe which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> puts upon them, cannot be the true ſenſe of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is, that our Saviour by pronouncing theſe words <hi>this is my Body,</hi> made that to be his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:62728:38"/> which before was only Bread; but certainly the literal ſenſe of the words does not import any thing of this, and it's the literal ſenſe which they muſt ſtick to, or elſe the whole ſupport of their cauſe is gone; now according to all the Rules of ſpeaking it ought to have been his Body before he could truly pronounce it to be ſo; but this they deny, and ſay it was only Bread till theſe words were pronounced, and that the calling it his Body made it become ſo; which is a form of Speech quite unknown to the World, and I challenge them to bring any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor either Sacred or Prophane that ever made uſe of words of this kind in ſuch a Senſe.</p>
            <p>Since therefore it is confeſſed that what our Saviour took into his Hands was <hi>Bread,</hi> and that it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:62728:39"/> 
               <hi>Bread</hi> till the ſpeaking of theſe words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> and ſince thoſe words in their natural conſtruction cannot be underſtood to <hi>effect</hi> any Change; it muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main <hi>Bread</hi> ſtill; and be only the <hi>Body of Chriſt</hi> in ſuch a ſenſe as <hi>Bread</hi> may be called his <hi>Body,</hi> that is in ſuch a ſenſe as the <hi>Lamb</hi> they eat of but juſt before was called the <hi>Paſſover;</hi> by being a Repreſentation and Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another Argument I would make uſe of is this, that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour did not by pronouncing thoſe words make what he gave them to be his very <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> becauſe after the pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of them, he calls what he gave in the <hi>Cup</hi> the <hi>Fruit of the Vine. Verily I ſay unto you I will drink no more of the Fruit of the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:62728:39"/> Vine, until that day that I drink it new in the Kingdom of God;</hi> In which words are contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed theſe <hi>three,</hi> I think, plain <hi>Reaſons,</hi> which prove, that it was <hi>Wine</hi> and not his <hi>Blood</hi> that he gave them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That He expreſly calls it the <hi>fruit of the Vine,</hi> and the Words, they ſay, are to be taken in the lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Senſe, and literally nothing elſe is the fruit of the Vine but <hi>Wine,</hi> at leaſt, the Blood of Chriſt is not.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In his ſaying that he would drink no <hi>more</hi> of it till he drank it new in the Kingdom of God, it is ſuppoſed that he had heretofore drank of what he then gave them. But I ſuppoſe, it will hardly be ſaid, that he ever before drank his own Blood.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:62728:40"/>
            <p n="3">3. As the Words ſuppoſe that he had drank before of what he then gave them, ſo they do that he would drink of it again; which very likely muſt be underſtood of his <hi>eating and drinking with them after his Reſurreſtion,</hi> for then the Kingdom of God, that is, the new State of the Chriſtian Church, was come. And therefore unleſs the Blood of Chriſt can be properly called the <hi>fruit of the Vine;</hi> unleſs it can be ſuppoſed that he had drank his own Blood before, and did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to drink it afterward, theſe Words muſt evince, that it was Wine which he then gave them.</p>
            <p>I would not conceal that tho' St. <hi>Matthew</hi> and St. <hi>Mark,</hi> recite the Words which I have Quoted, after the Conſecration of the Cup, yet one of the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> St. <hi>Luke</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:62728:40"/> recites them before, and ſo they may ſeem to relate to a Cup that went about the Table at the <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal Supper.</hi> But this Objection, if well conſidered, does rather the more confirm what I have been proving; for two of the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts do place it immediately after the Conſecration and delivery of the <hi>Sacramental Cup,</hi> and in them it is apparent they can referr to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but that. Now if our Opinion about this Sacrament, be true, the difference betwixt the Evangeliſts in this Caſe, is not material, as importing no difference at all in the Doctrine of the Sacrament, though our Saviour's Words are reported different ways, and ſo this ſecures the Honour and Authority of all the Evangeliſts. But if our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's Words are to be underſtood as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> underſtands
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:62728:41"/> them, it's impoſſible in any tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manner to reconcile the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts; for St. <hi>Matthew</hi> and St. <hi>Mark,</hi> muſt, upon this ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not only put his Words wrong together, and out of that order he ſpoke them, but muſt alſo quite miſrepreſent his meaning, and that in a Point of great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence: Which, I believe, can be no way conſiſtent with the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion which the Church of God has always had of theſe <hi>Goſpels.</hi> But I ſhall conſider this Matter a little more fully in that which I have to urge in the <hi>Third Place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. I deſire it may be conſidered that the Words of our Saviour in the Inſtitution of this Sacrament cannot be underſtood <hi>literally,</hi> becauſe as they are recited by the Evangeliſts they are not <hi>literally</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:62728:41"/> the ſame, but differ as to the <hi>lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> meaning very materially. <note place="margin">Mat. 26.28. Mark 14.24. Luke 22.20.</note> St. <hi>Matthew</hi> and St. <hi>Mark</hi> in the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtution of the Cup recite our Saviour's Words thus, <hi>This is my Blood of the New Teſtament which is ſhed for you;</hi> St. <hi>Luke</hi> recites them thus, <hi>This is the New Teſtament in my Blood.</hi> Now from this difference among them, I would obſerve theſe <hi>Two Things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> being ſo little curious to recite the very ſame Words that our Saviour ſpake, could not have any Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a ſtrict neceſſity of a literal meaning, and of ſuch a ſtrange Doctrine which could have no foundation but in the literal inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the very Words that he ſpake; this had been at beſt very ſtrange negligence in a
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:62728:42"/> Matter of ſo great Conſequence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I would obſerve that if our Interpretation of the Words be true, the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> are eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled, as agreeing in the ſame general Senſe tho' differing in the Expreſſions; becauſe both of them denote a Commemoration of the Blood of Chriſt, and of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> or <hi>Covenant</hi> founded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it; and it is not, then, very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial which is placed firſt; but if they are to be taken <hi>literaly</hi> it's impoſſible ever to make them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree; and ſo one of the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> muſt not only have miſ-recited our Saviour's Words; but quite have miſ-underſtood his meaning, and have done what he could to lead People wrong in a great Point of Faith: For certainly the <hi>true, real</hi> Blood of Chriſt is a very diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent thing from the New <hi>Covenant</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:62728:42"/> or <hi>Testament</hi> which is founded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But it</hi> will appear ſtill of greater Conſequence to keep to the very Words which Chriſt ſpake if the Opinion of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> be true, that it is the repeating the Words of our Saviour which <hi>effects</hi> the <hi>Tranſubstantiation.</hi> For I would ask, Suppoſing a Man ſhould Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate with the Words of St. <hi>Luke, This Cup is the New Teſtament in my Blood,</hi> would that change the <hi>Wine</hi> (not to ſay the <hi>Cup</hi>) into the very <hi>Blood</hi> of Chriſt? Certainly it would not do it by force of thoſe Words, for they intimate no ſuch thing; and it is not unlikely but thoſe were the very Words our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> ſpake, for not only St. <hi>Luke</hi> uſes them, but St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and that upon a ſolemn occaſion when it concerned him much to give a true
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:62728:43"/> Repreſentation of this Sacrament; as you may ſee, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> Chap. 11. The occaſion of his mentioning the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of this Sacrament was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great Irreverence, which ſome were guilty of in receiving of it, indeed ſuch, as it was almoſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for them to be guilty of, had they believed what the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> now believes about it; it was therefore very neceſſary that the Apoſtle ſhould ſpeak clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and plainly out <hi>in this matter;</hi> and we ſee he does ſolemnly uſher in what he ſays with the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Chriſt, <hi>For I have received of the Lord, that which I alſo deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto you, in</hi> &amp;c. And then he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats the Words as St. <hi>Luke</hi> does; and not only ſo, but calls the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part of the Sacrament <hi>Bread</hi> near Ten times in that Chapter.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:62728:43"/>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>Laſt Argument</hi> I ſhall make uſe of upon this Head, is this, That the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> upon another ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count does not agree with the Words of our Bleſſed Saviour. The Opinion of that Church is, That under each <hi>Species,</hi> as they call it, whole <hi>Chriſt</hi> is contained, <hi>Body, Blood, Soul,</hi> and <hi>Divinity;</hi> ſo that both are but juſt the very <hi>ſame Thing,</hi> in nothing different, but in outward <hi>appearance,</hi> which only deceives our Senſes. And it is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Opinion chiefly, that they ground the denyal of the <hi>Cup</hi> to the People; becauſe, ſay they, ſhould they have the <hi>Cup,</hi> they would have no more, but juſt the very ſame thing they had in the other Kind: And ſuppoſing their Opinion true, the Argument may, for any thing I know, have ſome force in it; but then they ought
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:62728:44"/> not to deny us leave to Argue the other way; That, that Opinion muſt needs be falſe, which makes our Saviour guilty of a great Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity in appointing Two <hi>Kinds,</hi> but both really the <hi>ſame thing,</hi> and one of them perfectly unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</p>
            <p>But that which I would chiefly take notice of, is, That this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of theirs, contradicts the <hi>Words</hi> of our Saviour, for what they make but <hi>One Thing</hi> he plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly makes <hi>Two,</hi> and calls them by <hi>Two</hi> different Names. The one he calls his <hi>Body,</hi> the other he calls his <hi>Blood,</hi> which ſuppoſes them to be <hi>Two</hi> different Things, as plain as Words can expreſs them.</p>
            <p>They ſay indeed, That in the <hi>Glorified Body of Chriſt,</hi> the Body and Blood cannot be ſeparated, and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:62728:44"/> therefore were the Words to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in ſuch a ſenſe as to conſider them ſeparated, they would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a great Abſurdity; ſo that wherever the one is, the other by <hi>concomitancy</hi> muſt be there too.</p>
            <p>But who told them, that the <hi>Glorified</hi> Body of Chriſt is in the Sacrament? The Words of the Inſtitution intimate no ſuch thing, but ſpeak of his Body <hi>given</hi> and his Blood <hi>ſhed,</hi> which certainly was <hi>ſeparate</hi> from his Body. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, this is arguing from Reaſon againſt the Words, and is juſt the very ſame thing which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn as <hi>Heretical</hi> in us; And if this be once allowed, they muſt throw off the whole Doctrine; for we can ſhew them Ten times as many Abſurdities in the Doctrine of <hi>Tranſustantiation,</hi> as they can in ſuppoſing the Body and Blood
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:62728:45"/> of Chriſt to ſubſiſt ſeparately.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, either we muſt ſtick to the very Words of our Bleſſed Saviour, or we muſt not; if we muſt, their Opinion muſt be falſe; which makes what our Saviour calls <hi>Two</hi> Things, to be but <hi>One;</hi> if we muſt not ſtick to the very Words, but interpret them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to right Reaſon and other Places of Scripture, they then give up their Cauſe.</p>
            <p>To conclude this Head, What Reaſon can there be imagined why our Saviour ſhould in a ſolemn manner, at different Times, and under different Names, give the very ſame thing? call the one his <hi>Body,</hi> and the other his <hi>Blood,</hi> when according to the Nature of the Thing he might as well have inverted the Names, and have
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:62728:45"/> called that his <hi>Blood,</hi> which he calls his <hi>Body,</hi> and ſo on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide. There cannot, I believe, be any Reaſon thought of but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this, That the one Kind, the <hi>Bread,</hi> was very proper to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the breaking of his Body; the other the <hi>Wine,</hi> to repreſent the ſhedding of his Blood; which is the very thing that we would have; for then there is a ſufficient Reaſon for theſe Names without any <hi>Bodily</hi> Preſence at all.</p>
            <p>I have been the longer in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the Senſe of the <hi>Scripture</hi> in this Matter, becauſe your Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters commonly boaſt more of the Scripture being for you in this Caſe, than in any other Controverſies betwixt us: And, I think, I have proved more than I need have done, in proving that the Senſe your Church puts upon the Words
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:62728:46"/> of our Saviour, <hi>cannot</hi> be the true Senſe of them: It being ſufficient in a Matter of this Nature, which is loaded with ſo many Abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to have ſhewed that they did <hi>fairly</hi> admit of another Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>But having ſo fully Confuted this Doctrine out of the Scriptures, I am now more at liberty to ſhew you the groſs Abſurdities and the monſtrous Contradictions that are involved in it; tho' in truth, it is ſo full fraught with Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that it's a hard matter to know where to begin; I ſhall therefore content my ſelf juſt to repeat ſome of them which are ready Collected to my hand, by a Great Divine of our own.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chilligworth,</hi> p. 165.</note> That there ſhould be Accidents without a
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:62728:46"/> Subject, that is, That there ſhould be, length and nothing long, breadth and nothing broad, thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and nothing thick, whiteneſs and nothing white, roundneſs and nothing round, weight and nothing heavy, ſweetneſs and nothing ſweet, moiſture and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing moiſt, fluidneſs and nothing flowing, many actions and no a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, many paſſions and no pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, that is, that there ſhould be a long, broad, thick, white, round, heavy ſweet, moiſt, flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, active, paſſive nothing.</p>
               <p>That Bread ſhould be turned into the Subſtance of Chriſt, and yet not any thing of that Bread become any thing of Chriſt, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Matter, nor the Form, nor the Accidents of Bread, be made either the Matter or the Form or the Accidents of Chriſt.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:62728:47"/>
               <p>That Bread ſhould be turned into nothing, and at the ſame time with the ſame Action be turned into Chriſt, and yet that Chriſt ſhould not be nothing.</p>
               <p>That the ſame thing at the ſame time ſhould have it's juſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſions, and juſt diſtance of it's Parts one from another, and at the ſame time ſhould not have it, but all its Parts together in the felf-ſame Point.</p>
               <p>That the Body of Chriſt which is much greater ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained wholly in that which is leſs, and that not once only, but as many times over as there are Points in the Bread and Wine.</p>
               <p>That the ſame thing at the ſame time ſhould be wholly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove it ſelf, and wholly below it ſelf, within it ſelf and without
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:62728:47"/> it ſelf, on the right Hand and on the left Hand, and round about it ſelf,</p>
               <p>That the ſame thing at the ſame time ſhould move to and from it ſelf and lie ſtill; or that it ſhould be carried from one place to another through the middle ſpace, and yet not move.</p>
               <p>That to be One ſhould be to be undivided from it ſelf, and yet that one and the ſame thing ſhould be divided from it ſelf.</p>
               <p>That a finite thing may be in all Places at once.</p>
               <p>That there ſhould be no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty in our Senſes, and yet that we ſhould know ſome things certainly, and know nothing
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:62728:48"/>
[Corporal] but by our Senſes.</p>
               <p>That, that which is, and was long ago, ſhould now begin to be. That the ſame thing ſhould be before and after it ſelf.</p>
               <p>That it ſhould be poſſible that the ſame Man, for Example, You or I, may at the ſame time be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake at <hi>London,</hi> and not awake but aſleep at <hi>Rome;</hi> there run or walk, here not run or walk, but ſtand ſtill, ſit, or liedown; there ſtudy or write, here do nothing but dine or ſup; there ſpeak, here be ſilent; that he may in one place freeze with cold, in another burn with heat; that he may be drunk in one place, ſober in another; valiant in one place, a coward in another; a Thief in one place, and honeſt in another; that he may be a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:62728:48"/> and go to Maſs in <hi>Rome,</hi> a Proteſtant and go to Church in <hi>England;</hi> that he may die in <hi>Rome,</hi> and live in <hi>England;</hi> or dying in both Places, may go to Hell from <hi>Rome,</hi> and to Heaven from <hi>Fngland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the Body and Soul of Chriſt ſhould ceaſe to be where it was, and yet not go to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, nor be deſtroyed.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Theſe are ſome of thoſe mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Contradictions which are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved in this Doctrine of <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation;</hi> I ſhall only obſerve theſe few things more about this Matter, and then conclude this Point.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That you ought not for the <hi>avoiding of</hi> theſe Difficulties to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent your ſelves to believe in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:62728:49"/> that ſomehow or other, you don't know how, this Sacrament is the Body of Chriſt; for your Church has determined the Matter, that it is the very Body of Chriſt which was Born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and was afterward Crucified, and that there remains no <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of Bread but only <hi>this Body</hi> of Chriſt after Conſecration.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I would obſerve that none of theſe Difficulties are taken off by conſidering Chriſt's Body as <hi>glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi> for beſides, that if it be a <hi>Body</hi> ſtill, it muſt have the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of a Body, this Sacrament was Inſtituted while our Saviour lived in the World, and had juſt ſuch a Body as other Men, of the ſame bigneſs, and all other quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as to his Body the ſame. And therefore in interpreting theſe Words <hi>This is my Body,</hi> all the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:62728:49"/> Difficlties are ſtill the ſame as if he were now living; or as they would be, were they ſpoken of the Body of any other Man.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I deſire that you would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that you may be ſure we do not miſ-underſtand nor miſ-repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent your Opinion, becauſe theſe Abſurdities are what <hi>your own Divines</hi> take notice of, as well as <hi>ours,</hi> and do not pretend to be able to give any direct Anſwer to them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I would obſerve, That tho' theſe Contradictions are ſo appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and ſtaring that no Body that hears of this Doctrine can well miſs of them, yet they are new, and none of them ever heard of in the Church for many Hundred Years; from whence we inferr, that the Doctrine it ſelf was as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle heard of.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:62728:50"/>
            <p n="5">5. We do not find that any Chriſtian for many Hundred Years ever denied or diſputed the truth of this Doctrine, from whence we cannot but conclude, that it was then unknown in the Church; for it muſt have had ſtrange good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to eſcape without any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, when all the Articles of the Creed had been Diſputed round.</p>
            <p n="6">6. As this was not diſputed or denied by any Chriſtians, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was it objected againſt the Chriſtian Religion by any Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, not even by <hi>Julian</hi> himſelf, who, as being an <hi>Apoſtate,</hi> muſt have known all the Secrets of our Religion; whereas in truth, there had been Ten times more weight in this, than in all the Objections together which they made uſe of againſt Chriſtianity.</p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:62728:50"/>
            <p n="7">7. There were ſeveral things in the Primitive Church inconſiſtent with the belief of this Doctrine, in particular that of mixing <hi>Water</hi> with the Wine, the Water to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the <hi>People,</hi> as the Wine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented the Blood of Chriſt; of which St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> gives us a full Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.<note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Cypr.</hi> Epiſt. 63.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. I would obſerve, That the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> can aſſign no pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar neceſſity, or uſefulneſs of this Sacrament above others, that ſhould give a probable Reaſon of the mighty difference betwixt this and others, and of ſuch a ſtrange wonderful Diſpenſation as the <hi>eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Bleſſed Saviour himſelf:</hi> Nay, with them both <hi>Bapliſm</hi> and <hi>Confeſſion</hi> are eſteemed much more <hi>neceſſary,</hi> and the omiſſion of them
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:62728:51"/> more <hi>dangerous</hi> than the omiſſion of this Sacrament.</p>
            <p n="9">9. To conclude this whole Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I think, I have ſufficiently ſhewed that this Doctrine has no foundation in Scripture; I would have conſidered at large the Senſe of the Primitive Church in it; and I do not queſtion but to have been able very clearly to make out that it was a Doctrine quite unknown to the Church of God for many Ages; but that was not conſiſtent with the Brevity I am at preſent forced to uſe; I would therefore only obſerve this one thing, That we ought not to conclude this to have been the Doctrine of the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> only from ſome <hi>accidental</hi> or <hi>general Expreſſions</hi> which they ſometimes make uſe of; It's plain that none of them <hi>deſignedly</hi> treat of this Matter, or <hi>explain</hi> it to us,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:62728:51"/> none of them recite it among the <hi>Articles of their Faith,</hi> none of them take any notice of the <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties</hi> of it, no Chriſtians appear to have been <hi>ſhocked</hi> at this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and no Heathens to have <hi>Objected</hi> it; all which could hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have been avoided had this been the conſtant Doctrine of the <hi>Catholick. Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for <hi>General Expreſſions,</hi> the calling what they received the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that could not be avoided, the <hi>Nature of the thing</hi> requiring them even accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>our</hi> Opinion of this Matter: And we ſee that notwithſtanding we have made ſuch expreſs Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations againſt the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this Controverſy we expreſs our ſelves more <hi>cautiouſly,</hi> than we may ſuppoſe the <hi>Fathers</hi> would do before any Controverſy was mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:62728:52"/> ved about it, yet ſome general Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of our <hi>own Divines</hi> are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten turned againſt us by thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and there is no queſtion but were the Authors of them as Old as the <hi>Fathers,</hi> they would be as confidently quoted for the Proof of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> as any Sayings of the <hi>Fathers</hi> now are.</p>
            <p>And this ſhews us how this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, tho' monſtrous in it ſelf, might under the <hi>Covert</hi> of ſuch <hi>General Expreſſions,</hi> without any great ſtir or buſtle, <hi>inſenſibly</hi> creep into the Church, eſpecially in very <hi>Ignorant</hi> and <hi>Superſtitions</hi> Times; tho' after all, <hi>our Divines</hi> have ſufficiently traced the foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of it, and ſhewed the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs it made, and the oppoſition it met with in the World before it could be <hi>Eſtabliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:62728:52"/>
            <p>The next thing to be ſpoken to is the <hi>Idolatry of the Church of Rome. In the Sacrfice of the Maſs, and in the Invocation of the Bleſſed Virgin, and of other Saints,</hi> as it is <hi>practiſed</hi> in that <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Idolatry may be of <hi>two ſorts.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>I. When People worſhip any thing for the <hi>Supreme God,</hi> which really is not ſo.</item>
               <item>II. When they give that <hi>Worſhip</hi> to any <hi>Creature,</hi> which is due only to <hi>God,</hi> and which he has <hi>appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated</hi> to himſelf.</item>
            </list>
            <p>As to the firſt ſort of <hi>Idolatry</hi> that of Worſhiping ſome thing as the <hi>Supreme God</hi> which realy is not ſo, we do not charge the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with it, unleſs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:62728:53"/> the worſhipping of what is but <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> in the Sacrament inſtead of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> may come under that head; I ſay, <hi>perhaps</hi> here, becauſe I would not enter into any thing, beſides the main cauſe, that may be conteſted; for tho' <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> be <hi>God,</hi> and they worſhip ſome thing as <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> which is not ſo, yet the miſtake being chiefly about his <hi>Human Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> I would not poſitively affirm a thing which may bring on any diſpute, which is not to our purpoſe.</p>
            <p>This they do not deny, that they give the higheſt Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which they call <hi>Latria,</hi> to that Object, which they take in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their hands, and put into their Mouths in receiving this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; which I ſhall at preſent call <hi>Idolatry,</hi> but with a promiſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:62728:53"/> it whenſoever they ſhall anſwer the Reaſons I have given to prove that what they thus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore is only <hi>Bread and Wine;</hi> or whenever they ſhall give me a more proper Name, by which I may call that great Sin of giving the <hi>higheſt Divine Worſhip</hi> to a <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> The truth is, that ſuch a Worſhip may not only be called <hi>Idolatry,</hi> but the moſt abſurd and ſenſeleſs <hi>Idolatry,</hi> that ever the World fell into: But this I ſhall not now inſiſt upon, having ſpok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en ſo much already to that which is the foundation of it, the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other Matter in which we charge them with <hi>Idolatry,</hi> is, the <hi>Invocation</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin,</hi> and other <hi>Saints.</hi> Now in this we do not charge them with owning any of thoſe to be <hi>God,</hi> but only with
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:62728:54"/> giving them that Worſhip and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour which cannot lawfully be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to any thing which is but a <hi>Creature.</hi> In ſpeaking to this, I ſhall conſider theſe <hi>Two Things.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Whether the giving to a Creature the Worſhip due only to God, may not be properly termed <hi>Idolatry,</hi> tho' at the ſame time we pay that Worſhip, we own it not to be <hi>God,</hi> but a <hi>Creature?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Whether the <hi>Worſhip</hi> given to <hi>Saints</hi> by the <hi>Invocation practiſed</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> be of that ſort, ſuch as God has <hi>appropriated</hi> to himſelf, and conſequently ſuch as <hi>becomes Idolatrous</hi> when applied to a <hi>Creature.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. As to the firſt of theſe, Thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church cannot deny but it muſt be a very great Sin to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:62728:54"/> give the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of <hi>God</hi> to <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures;</hi> but they deny it to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly <hi>Idolatry.</hi> We on the other ſide, grant, that it is not <hi>Idolatry,</hi> in the higheſt ſenſe of the Word, and in the ſenſe in which they commonly underſtand it, <hi>viz.</hi> The owning a Creature to be God. So that ſo far we are agreed; but then we ſay, that Word may be uſed in a lower ſenſe, to denote what they grant to be a <hi>Sin,</hi> as well as we, but will not call it by that Name, ſo that our difference in this Matter, is only about the uſe of a Word.</p>
            <p>Now we think our ſelves in the right in the uſe of this Word, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe Accounts,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe we have no other Name to expreſs that which is not denied to be a very great Sin,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:62728:55"/> The giving <hi>God's Worſhip</hi> to <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures;</hi> and having no peculiar Name for it, we think it not improper to give it the Name of that Sin which is of neareſt <hi>affinity</hi> to it, and of the ſame <hi>general kind;</hi> as is done in many other Caſes. Thus our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour calls looking <hi>upon a Woman to luſt after her,</hi> by the name of <hi>Adultery,</hi> and the like. The next ſtep to owning a <hi>Creature</hi> to <hi>be God,</hi> is to give it the <hi>Worſhip</hi> due to <hi>God,</hi> and therefore we think it not at all improper to call theſe two Sins by the ſame general Name, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally having no Word in our Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, more proper by which we may expreſs it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We think our ſelves fully ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified in the expreſſion, becauſe the Scripture does every where charge the Heathen Worſhip of their <hi>Gods</hi> and <hi>Images</hi> in general,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:62728:55"/> with the Crime of <hi>Idolatry;</hi> tho nothing can be more apparent than that many of the Heathen owned only <hi>one Supreme God,</hi> and that all of them looked upon many of the <hi>Gods</hi> whom they Worſhipped, not as <hi>Supreme,</hi> but as Gods of an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior Nature,</hi> and had much the ſame Opinion of them, as the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts have now of <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> and had the very ſame <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences</hi> and <hi>excuſes</hi> for the <hi>Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping</hi> of them which the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> make uſe of to defend themſelves. They owned many of their Gods to have been <hi>born,</hi> and to have <hi>dyed,</hi> and it was hardly poſſible to look upon any ſuch, to be the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme God.</hi> In a Word, There is nothing more evident than this, that they had ſeveral <hi>Ranks,</hi> and <hi>Orders,</hi> and <hi>Degrees</hi> among their Gods, and it was impoſſible to look upon all theſe to be <hi>Supreme:</hi>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:62728:56"/> And yet the Scripture every where without any diſtinction, charges their <hi>whole Worſhip</hi> with <hi>Idolatry;</hi> and ſo do the <hi>Primitive Fathers,</hi> as well as the Scriptures; particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, they thought it to be <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> to throw a <hi>little Incenſe</hi> into the Fire before the <hi>Statues</hi> of their <hi>Emperors.</hi> From whence we may plainly inferr theſe Two Things;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That they thought that there might be <hi>Idolatry</hi> in giving ſuch Worſhip as was <hi>appropriated to God,</hi> to Creatures, tho' they were not pretended to be any thing elſe but <hi>Creatures,</hi> only Creatures high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exalted, and in high Favour with God, as Saints and Angels are ſuppoſed to be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That they looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the offering of <hi>Incenſe,</hi> to be a part of <hi>Worſhip appropriated to God,</hi>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:62728:56"/> and that could not be given to a <hi>Creature</hi> without the Crime of <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry;</hi> which is a Matter the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> have reaſon to conſider well of, who offer it every Day to thoſe, who however they may have been better <hi>Men,</hi> are certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no more <hi>Gods</hi> than the <hi>Heathen Emperors</hi> were.</p>
            <p>To conclude this Matter, The ſenſe of the <hi>Primitive Church</hi> in the buſineſs of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> is plainly ſeen in this, that they every where ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the <hi>Arians</hi> of <hi>Idolatry</hi> for <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> for this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Reaſon, becauſe they owned him not to be <hi>God,</hi> or at leaſt, not the <hi>Supreme God;</hi> from whence it plainly appears, that they had the ſame Notions in this Caſe, that we now have, That Men may be guilty of <hi>Idolatry</hi> in giving <hi>Divine Worſhip</hi> to what they believe is not <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:62728:57"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> calls <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs Idolatry;</hi> which tho' it be a figurative Expreſſion, yet however, denotes to us the thing for which I am now pleading. The Covetous Man does not look upon his <hi>Money</hi> to be his <hi>God,</hi> or intend to give it any of that <hi>Worſhip</hi> he thinks due to <hi>God;</hi> I believe no Covetous Man in the World can be juſtly charged with either of theſe; but becauſe he places his <hi>Heart</hi> and his <hi>Affections</hi> upon it, which ought to be given to none but God; becauſe his Money is the thing in which he puts his <hi>truſt</hi> and his <hi>confidence,</hi> therefore it is, that he is ſaid to make an <hi>Idol</hi> of it, and to be guilty of <hi>Idolatry:</hi> And ſo it is as to the Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of <hi>Saints,</hi> tho' their Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers know very well that they are not <hi>Gods,</hi> yet becauſe they give
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:62728:57"/> them the Worſhip of <hi>God,</hi> that outward <hi>Adoration,</hi> and inward <hi>Reverence, hope, truſt,</hi> and <hi>depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance</hi> which are due only to <hi>God,</hi> they do by that make them <hi>Idols,</hi> and are juſtly chargeable with <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I now proceed to the <hi>Second Point,</hi> To ſhew, that the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> gives to the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Saints,</hi> by the <hi>Invocation pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed</hi> among them, is <hi>Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> ſuch as ought to be given to none but <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are not concern'd at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, to enquire into the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but into the <hi>Practice;</hi> that being the thing particularly Cenſur'd in the <hi>Teſt-Act;</hi> tho' indeed, the <hi>Practice</hi> of any Church, is the beſt Expoſition
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:62728:58"/> of Her <hi>Doctrine.</hi> The <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent</hi> leaves this Matter in general Terms, determines that we muſt <hi>ſeek the help and aid of the Saints,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Opem Auxili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>. Seſs. 25.</note> but does not fix the meaſures of it: However, ſince it does not Cenſure what was then the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Practice of that Church, we may take it for granted, that the meaning of the <hi>Council</hi> was, that we muſt <hi>ſeek their aid and help</hi> in the <hi>Methods</hi> which were then in <hi>uſe;</hi> for if they diſapproved of what was then commonly Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, it concerned them much to ſpeak out, as to ſet their own Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple right, and to keep them out of dangerous Practices; ſo alſo to vindicate the Honour of their Church, which was then openly charged with <hi>Idolatry</hi> upon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of thoſe Practices.</p>
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:62728:58"/>
            <p>We agree with the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in this, That we ought to have a great <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>reſpect</hi> for the <hi>Saints</hi> of God. That we ought to <hi>love</hi> their Memory, to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to imitate the good Examples they have left us, and to bleſs God for the Benefits he has beſtowed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Church by their means.</p>
            <p>And above <hi>other Saints,</hi> we ought to have a great eſteem and value for the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin,</hi> who had the Honour to be the <hi>Mother</hi> of our <hi>Lord,</hi> and by that, to be ſo nearly concerned in the greateſt Bleſſing that ever was beſtowed upon the World,</p>
            <p>But we differ from that Church in this, That they <hi>Adore</hi> the <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Pray</hi> to them; and that not as one <hi>Friend</hi> would deſire another to <hi>Pray</hi> for him, but with all the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:62728:59"/> 
               <hi>ſolemn</hi> Ceremonies and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Prayer, and with the very ſame with which they pray to <hi>God;</hi> they do it in their <hi>Churches, Kneeling,</hi> and with their <hi>Eyes lift up to Heaven,</hi> and with all the ſigns of <hi>Devotion</hi> which can be ſhewed, not only from one Creature to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but from a <hi>Creature to its Creator.</hi> They make <hi>Vows</hi> to them; burn <hi>Incenſe</hi> to their <hi>Images; dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate</hi> themſelves to their <hi>Service;</hi> make <hi>Offerings</hi> to them, and the like.</p>
            <p>They pray to them directly to beſtow Bleſſings upon them. Thus in the Office of the <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin,</hi> She is not only cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Gate of Heaven,</hi> but ſhe is intreated to <hi>looſe the bonds of the Gvilty,</hi> to <hi>give light to the Blind, and to drive away our Evils, and to ſhew her ſelf to be a Mother.</hi> They
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:62728:59"/> pray to her therein, for <hi>Purity of Life,</hi> and <hi>a ſafe Conduct to Heaven.</hi> She is commonly called the <hi>Queen of Heaven,</hi> the <hi>Mother of Mercy,</hi> and which is moſt Shameful of all, The <hi>Pſalms of David,</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed for the <hi>Honour</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and which contain the higheſt ſtrains of <hi>Devotion</hi> which a <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> can give to <hi>God,</hi> are by a <hi>Saint</hi> of that Church <note place="margin">Bonaventura</note> turned to the Honour of the <hi>Virgin,</hi> by putting <hi>her</hi> Name where the Name of <hi>God</hi> is put by <hi>David:</hi> And this was neither Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by the <hi>Council of Trent,</hi> nor has been by any <hi>Pope,</hi> that I can hear of, to this Day; but on the contrary, the Author of it has been <hi>Canonized,</hi> and the Book is in <hi>Common uſe,</hi> which perhaps, is one of the <hi>blackeſt</hi> pieces of <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> that ever was in the VVorld. And tho' a Church muſt not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:62728:60"/> bear the Guilt of what is pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd by private Perſons in her Communion, tho' it do paſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Cenſure; Yet conſidering how careful that Church has been in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Matters of much leſs moment eſpecially where her <hi>own Authority</hi> is concerned, and how ſolicitous they are to keep Books that make againſt them, out of the Hands of their People, it looks at leaſt, like <hi>eſpouſing the Blaſphemies,</hi> and <hi>Idolatrous Prayers and Praiſes</hi> of it, to let this Book go ſo freely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout without <hi>Cenſure,</hi> and to <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage</hi> it ſo far, as to make the <hi>Author</hi> of it a <hi>Saint.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe, and many other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, might be given of the <hi>Worſhip</hi> they give to the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin;</hi> and tho' they are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more <hi>modeſt,</hi> with relation to other <hi>Saints;</hi> yet what I have
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:62728:60"/> taken notice of already, may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently ſhew, that they give them the VVorſhip which God has ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to himſelf. I would only therefore mention further, that in many Inſtances, they pray to them to beſtow thoſe Bleſſings which only God can give, ſuch as to <hi>open the Gates of Heaven,</hi> to <hi>unty the bonds of their Iniquity, to heal their ſpiritual Maladies;</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the ſame Nature, of which, I ſhall give them Examples at large, if required, or, if I find it neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to confirm any thing that I have now ſaid.</p>
            <p>I <hi>now proceed</hi> to take notice of ſome of thoſe Reaſons we have to prove, that this <hi>Invocation</hi> is part of that <hi>Worſhip</hi> which God has <hi>appropriated</hi> to himſelf, and which conſequently cannot be given to any <hi>Creature,</hi> without the Crime of <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:62728:61"/>
            <p n="1">1. I deſire it may be conſidered, that the Scripture does every where ſpeak of <hi>Prayer</hi> as applied to <hi>God,</hi> and to none elſe, and that without the leaſt intimation of any ſuch <hi>Diſtinctions</hi> as are made uſe of in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> VVe have in the <hi>Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> the Hiſtory of the Church of God, for near 4000 Years; and in all that time, there is not the leaſt inſtance, or intimation, of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Prayer</hi> put up to any <hi>Creature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be it will be ſaid, That the <hi>Saints</hi> were not then in <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and ſo were not in a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>hear</hi> the Prayers that ſhould be put up to them, and had not ſo much <hi>Favour</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> as they may be ſuppoſed to have now, ſince the <hi>Reſurrection of Chriſt,</hi> that he has admitted them ſo nearly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Preſence.</p>
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:62728:61"/>
            <p>Now in Anſwer to this, I ſhall not at preſent, pretend to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, whether the <hi>Saints</hi> of the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> were in <hi>Heaven</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Chriſt's Reſurrection,</hi> or not; nor whether <hi>they,</hi> and other <hi>Saints</hi> ſince are there now; becauſe a great many Chriſtians of no mean Authority in the Church of God, have been of different Opinions in theſe Matters; only I think theſe two or three Things, are very plain.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> were ſuppoſed by a great many, before our Saviour's time, to be in <hi>Heaven;</hi> and they muſt have been looked upon by them, to be very great <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> by being taken out of this World in ſo ſtrange and wonderful a manner, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture tells us they were; and yet we hear as little of <hi>praying</hi> to
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:62728:62"/> them, as to any other Perſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Suppoſing it not agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then, whether <hi>Saints</hi> were in <hi>Heaven,</hi> yet all agreed that the <hi>Angels</hi> were. And they were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together as well capacitated to hear and anſwer Prayers, which ſhould have been put up to them then, as they are <hi>now,</hi> and yet we find as little of Mens <hi>praying</hi> to <hi>Angels,</hi> as they did to <hi>Saints</hi> in thoſe Times.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whatever Reaſon can be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for <hi>praying to Creatures now,</hi> would have held as well <hi>then;</hi> whatever <hi>neceſſity,</hi> or <hi>conveniency,</hi> or <hi>advantage,</hi> or <hi>fitneſs</hi> there may be in it, were all the ſame, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed much greater then, than they are now, upon theſe Two Accounts,</p>
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:62728:62"/>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe the <hi>Christian Religion</hi> is of it ſelf a State of much <hi>greater Perfection</hi> than any Diſpenſation that was before it. God has in it revealed himſelf more clearly and plainly to the World, has more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videnced his Love and Tenderneſs to Mankind, has given us greater incouragements to draw near to him; He ſpeaks to us in the Goſpel as a Father to his Children, as a <hi>reconciled Father in Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and therefore accordingly, in that Form of Prayer which our Saviour has left us, that is the Appellation which he has taught us to make uſe of, <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven;</hi> Now, why ſhould a Child be afraid to approach the Preſence of his Father? Or, what need has he of any body to introduce him? Under the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Diſpenſation, when the Law was given with <hi>Thunderings and Lightnings,</hi> when
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:62728:63"/> God was called by the terrible Name of the <hi>Lord of Hoſts,</hi> there might be more reaſon to think of ſome body to introduce them to his Preſence; which yet we do not find was ever recommended, or practiſed among them: How much more may Chriſtians <hi>come with boldneſs to the Throne of Mercy,</hi> and expect to find <hi>Grace to help in time of need?</hi> But what is more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable:</p>
            <p n="2">2. Chriſtians have <hi>Chriſt</hi> for their <hi>Mediator, who is able to ſave to the uttermoſt all thoſe that come to God by him;</hi> He is in Heaven ready to plead their cauſe, and to get their Prayers heard, and their Perſons ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted; and they that have ſuch an <hi>Advocate,</hi> need not fly to any elſe. But it was not ſo with the <hi>Church</hi> before <hi>Christ;</hi> and therefore if the thing had been at all lawful, they
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:62728:63"/> had much more reaſon to make <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels</hi> their <hi>Patrons,</hi> than Chriſtians have. And yet we ſee that in the Account which we have in the <hi>Bible</hi> of the Church of God before Chriſt for near 4000 Years, there is not the leaſt hint of any thing of this kind.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What I have ſaid already, that all along in the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> Prayer is appropriated to God, and that without any <hi>reſerve,</hi> or <hi>diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> may be ſufficient to ſhew the Mind of God in that Caſe: But I have this further to add, That the ſame Scripture, adds with the ſame general words, condemn as <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous</hi> all the <hi>Old Heathen Worſhip:</hi> Now I have ſhewed before, that much of this <hi>Worſhip</hi> was paid to <hi>Creatures,</hi> under the ſame Notions and Apprehenſions, that thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> Worſhip <hi>Saints</hi>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:62728:64"/> and <hi>Angels;</hi> indeed there was this difference, that moſt of thoſe Worſhipped in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> were probably <hi>good Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> as moſt of thoſe whom the <hi>Heathens</hi> Worſhipped, were <hi>bad</hi> ones, and it may be <hi>Devils:</hi> But this diſtinction of <hi>good</hi> or <hi>bad Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> may make the Worſhip more or leſs <hi>Impious,</hi> but not more or leſs <hi>Idolatrous;</hi> whatever will make it <hi>Idolatry</hi> in the one Caſe, will make it ſo in the other. The Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <hi>appropriated to God,</hi> is no more due to a <hi>good</hi> Creature, than it is to a <hi>bad</hi> one; ſince therefore I have ſhewed, that the Scripture every where condemns the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which the Heathen gave to what they owned not to be <hi>God,</hi> and which they did not intend to Worſhip as the Supreme God; I ſay, ſince this is condemned, not only as <hi>Impious,</hi> for chooſing ill
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:62728:64"/> 
               <hi>Creatures,</hi> but as <hi>Idolatrous</hi> for giving what belonged only to <hi>God:</hi> this muſt equally prove all <hi>Creature Worſhip</hi> to be <hi>Idolatrous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. This Creature Worſhip, is as litle heard of in the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> as it is in the <hi>Old.</hi> Heard of, it is indeed, but what approbation it met with, we may ſee by conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe particulars.</p>
            <p>The <hi>firſt</hi> Inſtance is that of the <hi>Devil</hi> deſiring our <hi>Saviour to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him,</hi> upon promiſe to give him <hi>all the Kingdoms of the World:</hi> But let us ſee what our Saviour anſwers; he does not put him off with tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him either the <hi>Dignity</hi> of his own Perſon, or the unfitneſs of the thing, in Worſhipping him becauſe he was a Devil; but he gives ſuch a Reaſon as will hold againſt all Worſhipping of <hi>Creatures.
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:62728:65"/> Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi> From which words, I would obſerve theſe Two Things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Worſhip which the <hi>Devil</hi> deſires, and which our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> ſays muſt be given <hi>only</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> was not to <hi>offer Sacrifice</hi> to him, which the Writers of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> make the only outward Worſhip appropriated to God, but it was to <hi>fall down</hi> and <hi>adore</hi> him; from whence we may inferr, that to <hi>fall down</hi> and <hi>adore</hi> any Creature, muſt be Idolatry, which part of Worſhip its apparent the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> give to their <hi>Saints and Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. I would obſerve here, that the Devil did not pretend to be the <hi>Supreme God,</hi> but plainly the contrary; for when he ſhews our
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:62728:65"/> Saviour all the Kingdoms of the World, he tells him, that all theſe things were <hi>given</hi> to him, <hi>Luke.</hi> 4.6. in which he plainly profeſſes, not a <hi>Supreme,</hi> But a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legated</hi> Power; ſo that had not our Saviour in his Anſwer, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the Worſhip of <hi>Creatures,</hi> tho' <hi>owned and acknowledged</hi> to be <hi>Creatures,</hi> he had not given a full Anſwer to the Devil, for the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> did not deſire to be <hi>Worſhipped</hi> as the <hi>Supreme God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Inſtance we have of this kind, is that of St. <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Revelations</hi> falling down to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the <hi>Angel,</hi> who we ſee puts him off it, with the ſame kind of general Words, that our Saviour uſes in the former Inſtance, <hi>See thou do it not, I am thy fellow ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, Worſhip God,</hi> Rev. 22.18.19. Here I would obſerve, as in
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:62728:66"/> the former Caſe, that the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which the Angel <hi>rejects,</hi> and <hi>appropriates to God,</hi> is falling down at his feet to Adore him. And in the next place, I would obſerve, that had Adoration been due to an Angel, the true Anſwer to St. <hi>John</hi> had been, that he ſhould have a care not to miſtake him to be <hi>God,</hi> who was but an <hi>Angel,</hi> and ſo give him more than was due to him; but we ſee he throws off the whole without any reſerve or diſtinction, and for a Reaſon that will hold againſt all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Worſhip, that he was his <hi>Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-ſervant.</hi> In a word, it had been no great ſecret for the Angel to tell St. <hi>John,</hi> that <hi>God</hi> was to be <hi>Worſhipped,</hi> or that <hi>God only</hi> was to be Worſhipped with an <hi>inward apprehenſion,</hi> of his being <hi>God,</hi> neither of theſe were any great Myſtery, or to the purpoſe.
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:62728:66"/> And therefore his meaning muſt be, that Religious Worſhip, ſuch as that Adoration was, ought to be given to none but God.</p>
            <p>I ſhall name but one more place of Scripture, in which this <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Worſhip</hi> is taken notice of, and that is <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.18. <hi>Let no man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile you of your reward by a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary humility, and Worſhipping of Angels.</hi> The Apoſtle in this, and the following Verſes, makes uſe of Two Arguments againſt the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of Angels. Firſt, that it is a <hi>voluntary</hi> Humility, that is, tho' Men may pretend a great deal of Humility, that it is not fit for ſuch mean Creatures as they to go directly into the Preſence of God, but that they ought to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to the Angels of God to be their Introducers; yet all this, is Humility of their own inventing,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:62728:67"/> ſuch as God has not required at their hands.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That this Worſhipping of Angels, is <hi>leaving Chriſt their Head;</hi> He is the <hi>only Mediator betwixt God and Men,</hi> and therefore ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying to any other, is leaving him who is the Head of the Church; and then no wonder if it <hi>beguile us of our reward.</hi> This Argument is very plain and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtrong againſt the practice of Praying to <hi>Saints</hi> or <hi>Angels,</hi> and it hath this one thing very obſervable in it, That if this Text proves it unlawful to ſet up any more <hi>Mediators</hi> but <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> it muſt be underſtood of <hi>Mediators of Interceſſion,</hi> for no body could ſo much as pretend, that <hi>Angels</hi> were <hi>Mediators</hi> of <hi>Redemption,</hi> as thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:62728:67"/> (without any ground at all) make the diſtinction.</p>
            <p>I might ſhew farther the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry</hi> of this Practice, of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> from this, that it muſt ſuppoſe <hi>Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections</hi> in the <hi>Creatures</hi> to whom we pray; as of <hi>Power</hi> to be able to ſupply our <hi>Wants,</hi> eſpecially, in thoſe Prayers that are put up to them directly to beg ſuch, or ſuch Bleſſings from them; and ſo of <hi>Knowledge,</hi> becauſe Prayer (at leaſt Mental Prayer) ſuppoſes that the Perſons we pray to, know our Hearts, and the ſecret thoughts, and ſincerity or inſincerity of all the Men and Women in the World, and that they can perfectly attend to them all at the ſame time; which are Perfections that the Scripture never attributes to any but God, and in the Nature of the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:62728:68"/> thing, it is hardly conceivable of any Creature; but I ſhall content my ſelf to have named theſe things, and ſhall conclude this whole Matter, with juſt propoſing thoſe two ſhort Conſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I deſire it may be conſidered, that in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> there is no External part of Religion <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable to Creatures,</hi> but the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Maſs,</hi> and if in the preceding Diſcourſes, I have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrown the foundation of that, there is then nothing at all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I deſire it may be conſidered, that the Reaſons commonly given to juſtify Prayers to <hi>Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> would, if well followed, hinder Men from ever praying to God at all, as in fact, this has
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:62728:68"/> much eſtranged Men from God in thoſe Countries where they have had no <hi>Proteſtants</hi> among them to make them aſhamed of it; and even nearer our ſelves, I believe, we may juſtly ſay, that at leaſt Ten Prayers are put up to Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures for one that is put up to God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Of the Pope's Supremacy.</note> I now come to conſider the <hi>Oath of Supremacy,</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of Two Parts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. A <hi>Declaration</hi> of the Unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, and <hi>Impiety</hi> of taking up Arms againſt the <hi>King</hi> upon Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of His, being <hi>Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> or <hi>Deprived</hi> by the <hi>Pope.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. A <hi>Renunciation</hi> of the <hi>Pope</hi>'s pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Supremacy</hi> over the Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> particularly over that part of it in this Kingdom.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="128" facs="tcp:62728:69"/>
            <p>As to the <hi>Firſt of theſe,</hi> I need not inſiſt upon it, becanſe if I can prove, the Second, <hi>That the Pope has of right no Spiritual Power</hi> here, the other muſt of courſe fall with it. I would only obſerve before I proceed, That if thoſe of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Communion</hi> among us, do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that the <hi>Pope</hi> has a Power <hi>from God</hi> to <hi>Excommunicate,</hi> and to <hi>Deprive</hi> Princes of their Kingdoms for <hi>Hereſy,</hi> and that therefore they are bound to <hi>concur</hi> with the <hi>Pope</hi> as far they can, to put his Sentence in <hi>Execution,</hi> this muſt make them <hi>Enemies</hi> to all <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, they have reaſon to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that Proteſtants ſhould have a care of them. But if they do believe that God has not given any ſuch Power to the <hi>Pope,</hi> they have then Reaſon to have a care of their <hi>Guide,</hi> who is doing what he can, under pretence of Authority from
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:62728:69"/> God, to carry them to <hi>Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Murther,</hi> and all the <hi>Villanies</hi> which muſt follow an attempt to turn out their <hi>King,</hi> and all his <hi>Proteſtant Subjects</hi> that will ſtand by him: But I have in ſome meaſure taken notice of theſe things alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and therefore ſhall not now inlarge upon them; but proceed to conſider the Grounds of the Popes pretence to <hi>Supremacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Opinion of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> with relation to his <hi>Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy</hi> is this, That <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> made <hi>Saint Peter</hi> the <hi>Supreme Governor</hi> and <hi>Head,</hi> as of all the reſt of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> ſo alſo of the <hi>whole Church;</hi> That St. <hi>Peter</hi> was afterward <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that by Divine Appointment his <hi>Succeſſors the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of Rome,</hi> are to enjoy the ſame <hi>Supremacy</hi> over the <hi>Church</hi> which he had.</p>
            <pb n="130" facs="tcp:62728:70"/>
            <p>Their Opinion about the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> is founded chiefly upon thoſe Words of our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18,19. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this Rock I will build my Church. — And I will give unto thee the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> They ſay, our Saviour does by theſe Words, promiſe to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> to make him <hi>Monarch</hi> of the whole Church: We ſay, that tho' theſe Words were ſpoken to St. <hi>Peter</hi> upon occaſion of his ſpeaking to our <hi>Saviour</hi> immediately before, yet, that this Promiſe does as much belong to the reſt of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> as it does to <hi>him,</hi> and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, whatever Power may be here promiſed to him over the <hi>Church,</hi> there is none promiſed over the reſt of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and that conſequently, his <hi>Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors</hi> can claim nothing from hence
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:62728:70"/> over the <hi>Succeſſors</hi> of all the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, the other Biſhops of the Chriſtian Church.</p>
            <p>But to conſider this Matter more particularly, we may take notice,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the reſt of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> did not apprehend that St. <hi>Peter</hi> had here any peculiar Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er promiſed him above them; for we find that not long after, they were contending, who ſhould be the <hi>greateſt;</hi> by which it's plain, they did not then apprehend that our Saviour had already determin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Matter: And as for our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> himſelf, he does not at all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to put them right, as it was of great conſequence he ſhould do, ſuppoſing that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned St. <hi>Peter</hi> for their <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour;</hi> but he endeavours to teach them all humility, and not to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:62728:71"/> Power or Authority over one another. And the ſame inſtance we have in the Caſe of <hi>Zebe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee's Children,</hi> when their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther came to deſire that the <hi>one might ſit on his right hand and the other on his left in his Kingdom,</hi> that is, that they might be the Perſons of chief Favour, and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority with him; their Petition plainly implies, that they knew nothing of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Prerogatives; and our <hi>Saviour</hi>'s Anſwer, which you may ſee at large, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20. im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies as plainly, that neither St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> nor any body elſe was to have ſuch Power in the Church, as the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> have ſince pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I would obſerve, that theſe Words of our <hi>Saviour</hi> to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> do not actually inveſt him with any Power, but are only a <hi>Promiſe</hi>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:62728:71"/> to him; and therefore the beſt way to ſee what was peculiar to him in it above the reſt of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> will be to ſee the <hi>fulfilling</hi> of the <hi>Promiſe,</hi> and his being <hi>Actually in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted</hi> in it. That this is only a <hi>Promiſe</hi> appears from the Words themſelves, which run in the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture tenſe, <hi>I will give thee the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven:</hi> And I believe, they of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> will not deny this, becauſe they ſay, that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were not <hi>Prieſts</hi> till our <hi>Saviour</hi> made them ſo in the Inſtitution of the <hi>Lord's Supper.</hi> Now if we conſider the <hi>Actual Inveſtiture</hi> into this Power, there is nothing peculiar to <hi>Saint Peter.</hi> Our <hi>Saviour</hi> gives them all their Power together, in Words much of the ſame Nature with that Promiſe before to St. <hi>Peter; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ye the Holy Ghoſt, whoſe ſoever ſins ye remit they are remitted, and
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:62728:72"/> whoſe ſoever ſins ye retain they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</hi> And as for the Expreſſion, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this Rock I will build my Church,</hi> there is much the ſame ſaid of all the <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> The Church is ſaid to be <hi>built upon the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Apoſtles, and Prophets, Jeſus Chriſt himſelf being the chief Corner-stone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The beſt way to ſee whether St. <hi>Peter</hi> had any ſuch <hi>Supremacy,</hi> will be to ſee whether he exerciſed any, whether he did any <hi>Acts,</hi> or <hi>Offices</hi> which belonged to ſo high a Power. There muſt be conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo many occaſions for the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of that Power, that if he had any ſuch we could not miſs of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of it. The Times of the Apoſtles were indeed, Times of greater <hi>Simplicity,</hi> than theſe later Ages; and therefore I do not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:62728:72"/> they ſhould ſhew me St. <hi>Peter</hi> Commanding after the manner of our <hi>Modern Popes:</hi> But if they can ſhew me any one ſingle Act of <hi>Authority</hi> over the reſt of the <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> if they can ſhew me St. <hi>Peter</hi> of himſelf, making Laws, and Orders for the good Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, or ſo much as <hi>preſiding</hi> in the <hi>College</hi> of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles;</hi> if they can ſhew me any <hi>Appeals</hi> made to him, or Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies ended by him, or, among ſo many Controverſies as happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, any advice to repair to him, or command to <hi>obey</hi> him; I ſhall not ſhut my Eyes againſt the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries. But to conſider this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a little more particularly: As ſoon as our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour</hi> was <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended,</hi> there was an occaſion gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to exerciſe this <hi>Supremacy</hi> in chuſing a new <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in the room of <hi>Judas, Acts</hi> 1. But we ſee that the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:62728:73"/> method taken was, that the whole Multitude choſe <hi>Two,</hi> and then they caſt <hi>Lots</hi> which of the <hi>Two</hi> ſhould be the <hi>Apoſtle.</hi> And ſo as to the chooſing of <hi>Deacons, Acts</hi> 7. the whole Multitude choſe them, and preſented them, not to <hi>Peter,</hi> but to all the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> to be <hi>Ordained.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we look a little further into the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles to Ch.</hi> 8. We ſhall find the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> not ſent by St. <hi>Peter</hi> up and down to their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs as occaſion required, but St. <hi>John</hi> and <hi>him</hi> ſent by them to <hi>Samaria;</hi> which was not very <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly</hi> nor very <hi>fit</hi> had they known him to be their <hi>Sovereign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 11. we find thoſe of the <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> contending with him, and forcing him to give an account of his Actions, and that without any <hi>Ceremony,</hi> or <hi>deference</hi> proper
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:62728:73"/> for one in ſo high a Place; and we ſee he patiently ſubmits to it, without ſtanding upon his Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative of being unaccountable, without chiding them for their Inſolence, or any thing of that kind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 15. we find a ſolemn <hi>Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Brethren</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks indeed, as any other Man might have done, but does not <hi>preſide</hi> or <hi>determine</hi> any thing. The <hi>Appeal</hi> was to the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Elders</hi> at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> not to <hi>him</hi> alone; and if any thing in the whole Meeting was done <hi>Authoritatively</hi> by any ſingle Perſon, it was by St. <hi>James,</hi> for he paſſes Sentence, as you may ſee <hi>Verſe</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>If we go to the <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> we ſhall find as little evidence of his
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:62728:74"/> Authority, as we have in the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the Church in the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt <hi>Epiſtle</hi> is that to the <hi>Romans,</hi> not from St. <hi>Peter,</hi> but from St. <hi>Paul;</hi> where there is not the leaſt notice taken either of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> or of the great <hi>Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives</hi> of that <hi>Church,</hi> which, one would think, could hardly be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided if St. <hi>Paul</hi> had known any thing of them; nay he ſays ſome things which directly contradict their Pretences, which you may ſee <hi>Chap.</hi> 11. He tells them there, that he ſpeaks <hi>to them who were Gentiles, as being the Apoſtle of the Gentiles;</hi> and if ſo, St. <hi>Peter</hi> muſt not have had ſo near a relation to them, becauſe he was the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> of the <hi>Jews.</hi> Then he proceeds to adviſe them to have a care of themſelves, leſt they ſhould fall
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:62728:74"/> away, and be cut off; as you may ſee <hi>ver.</hi> 20, 21. <hi>Be not high-minded, but fear, for if God ſpared not the natural Branches, take heed, leſt he alſo ſpare not thee.</hi> It's plain, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> at that time knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the great Privileges of that Church, of its being the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mistris of all Churches,</hi> of its being the <hi>Center</hi> of Church <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> and of its being <hi>Infallibly</hi> ſecured from <hi>Error</hi> and <hi>Apostacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we go on to the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> we ſhall ſind there a very proper occaſion to menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Authority, if he had any ſuch as they boaſt of, as you may ſee 1 <hi>Eph.</hi> Chap. 1. <hi>Now this I ſay that every one of you ſaith I am of</hi> Paul, <hi>and I of</hi> Apollos, <hi>and I of</hi> Cephas [or <hi>Peter</hi>] <hi>and I of Chriſt; Is Chriſt divided, or was</hi> Paul <hi>Crucified for you? &amp;c.</hi> Thoſe People certainly knew nothing of
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:62728:75"/> St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>Supremacy,</hi> nor St. <hi>Paul</hi> neither, otherwiſe he would hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have omitted to tell them of ſuch an <hi>Infallible Cure</hi> for their <hi>Diviſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Epiſtle of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Galatians</hi> we have many Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments againſt St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Supremacy;</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us there that he had no <hi>Superior,</hi> that he had his <hi>Authority</hi> from none but <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Ch. 1.17. He compares himſelf with St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and ſays that the <hi>Miniſtry of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion was committed to him as the Miniſtry of the Circumciſion was unto</hi> Peter. Ch. 2. v. 7. He men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions St. <hi>Peter</hi> as of the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority with <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John, when</hi> James Cephas <hi>and</hi> John <hi>who ſeemed to be Pillars,</hi> Verſe the 9th. And a little further he tells us how he openly withſtood <hi>Peter</hi> to
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:62728:75"/> the Face, <hi>becauſe he was to be blam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> All theſe things might be urg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at large, but I content my ſelf only tomention them. But from all together, I think, I may well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that this <hi>Promiſe</hi> of our <hi>Saviour</hi> did not intend St. <hi>Peter</hi> any Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over the reſt of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and conſequently, not any to his <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors</hi> (if he had any) over the <hi>Biſhops</hi> of the Chriſtian Church, who are <hi>Succeſſors</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> in general; tho' we do not deny, but St. <hi>Peter</hi> had a Power over the whole Church, but only as the <hi>reſt</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> had, whoſe <hi>Care,</hi> and conſequently <hi>Authority</hi> was not conſined to <hi>particular</hi> Churches, as it was thought fit in order to the better Government of the Church, that the Authority of <hi>Biſhops</hi> ſhould be ſince, but was left at large, and unconfin'd as to any certain limits either of Perſon, or Places.</p>
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:62728:76"/>
            <p>But ſuppoſe it ſhould be granted, that St. <hi>Peter</hi> had ſuch Power, as they affirm he had, yet there is not one Word in <hi>Scripture</hi> about a <hi>Succeſſor,</hi> or about the vaſt <hi>Privileges</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> in this Point. And in truth, there is as little evidence in the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the Church for many Ages, of this pretended Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> as there is in the <hi>Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rome</hi> was at the time of the Plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Chriſtian Religion, a vaſt City, and the <hi>Head</hi> of a very great <hi>Empire:</hi> This muſt of it ſelf, give the Biſhop of it a great influence in the Affairs of the Church, which was almoſt all within the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire; this made all ſort of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication with him eaſy, by means of the mighty refort that was made from all Parts to the
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:62728:76"/> tal City; and Greatneſs of his See, did in courſe of Time bring great Riches to it, and if we add to this, that it was honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the <hi>Preaching</hi> and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom</hi> of two great Apoſtles, St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> we ſee plain Reaſons why the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> were likely to make a great Figure in the Church; but as for <hi>real Authority,</hi> ſuch as is now pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, there do not appear any foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of it for ſeveral Ages.</p>
            <p>As for Speculative Opinions, We may not perhaps have ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain an account of them ſo long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, unleſs of thoſe which by ſome accident or other came to be Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted. But Government is a Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal thing, and there happens every day Occaſion to exerciſe it, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the Government of the <hi>whole</hi> Church; and if the <hi>Pope</hi> had been
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:62728:77"/> from the beginning what he pretends to be, and what he now makes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, his Power could have been no more a matter of Controverſy, than it could be made a Controverſy whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there were any <hi>Chriſtian Church;</hi> for the ſame Hiſtory that clears the one muſt at the ſame time clear the other.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Old Body</hi> of Hiſtory of the Chriſtian Church is that of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> which contains an account of the Affairs of it for above 300 Years; now if the Pope were <hi>Monarch</hi> of the Church for thoſe 300 Years, we can no more miſs to ſee it in that Hiſtory, than we can read any Hiſtory of <hi>England</hi> for ſuch a Number of Years, and be uncertain whether we had here any <hi>King</hi> or no, for ſo long a time: No Hiſtory hardly can be conceived ſo faulty or imperfect, as to leave ſuch a Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:62728:77"/> a Secret or uncertain; And yet I would Challenge any indifferent Perſon to read that <hi>Hiſtory</hi> over, and to ſhew me but any one thing in it from which it can be probably inferred, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> was the <hi>Governour</hi> of the <hi>whole</hi> Church; whereas, were it truly ſo, there muſt have been ſomething of it in almoſt every Page; Becauſe all the buſineſs of the Church muſt in a manner roul upon him. He muſt be the Perſon appeal'd to in almoſt all Difficulties, we muſt have found his decrees in all the great Affaires that paſſed, His Decretal Epiſtles muſt have been interſperſed up and down in the whole Work; his Authority muſt have put an end to all <hi>Schiſms</hi> and <hi>Hereſies,</hi> or at leaſt their <hi>Rebellion</hi> againſt him muſt have been reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as one great part of their Crime. In a word (as I ſaid before) the thing muſt have appeared as plain as that
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:62728:78"/> there was any <hi>King</hi> in <hi>England</hi> for theſe laſt 300 Years.</p>
            <p>Next to that <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> the moſt likely place to find his <hi>Authority,</hi> if he had any, is in the Works of St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> which contain more of the <hi>Ancient Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> of the Church, than is to be found in any other <hi>Old</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, eſpecially, if we add fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that a great part of his Works is only <hi>Letters</hi> to, or from <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of Rome.</hi> We could not but ſee, in ſuch a number of Letters, whether he wrote to his <hi>Sovereign</hi> or not; we ſhould ſee it in the <hi>Titles</hi> which he gives him, in his <hi>Style,</hi> in the deference which he pays him. In ſhort, the whole would ſome how or other ſhew that it was his <hi>Superior</hi> he was writing to, but now the contrary to this is true. He never ſpeaks to him, or of him in his Letters to
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:62728:78"/> other People, but by the Name of <hi>Brother;</hi> he freely Cenſures him and his Opinions, juſt as he would do by any other Man, and with as little deference or reſpect; and he finally differed from him in a Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of great conſequence, that of <hi>Re-baptizing Hereticks,</hi> and called <hi>Councils</hi> of the Clergy, and raiſed a great Party againſt him in it, and yet was never, that I have heard of, charged either with <hi>Rebellion,</hi> or <hi>Schiſm,</hi> or <hi>Hereſy</hi> upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; but is to this day reputed a <hi>Saint</hi> in <hi>Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude this Matter, The whole <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of the Ancient Univerſal <hi>Church,</hi> plainly ſhews that the <hi>Government</hi> of it was an <hi>Ariſtocracy,</hi> eſpecially, that ſtrict Account that <hi>Biſhops</hi> were to give to their Fellow <hi>Biſhops</hi> up and down the World, of their <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:62728:79"/> and their <hi>Faith,</hi> and other Matters in order to hold <hi>Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> with one another, which as it is left off ſince the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Authority came up, ſo the uſe of it muſt have been inconſiſtent with it, for it was taking the <hi>Judgment</hi> of <hi>Things</hi> and <hi>Perſons</hi> into their own Hands, which muſt not have belonged to them, but to the <hi>Sovereign High Prieſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, their <hi>forging</hi> ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Decretal Epiſtles</hi> for the <hi>Biſhops of Rome</hi> for ſo many <hi>Ages,</hi> is a plain Argument that they have no <hi>true</hi> Evidences of the exerciſe of ſuch Authority in the <hi>Ancient Church,</hi> as is now pretended to. Had ſuch Authority been then exerciſed they needed not have been put to the <hi>forging</hi> Evidences of it; we could not eaſily have miſs'd of as many true <hi>Decretal Epiſtles,</hi> as we have
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:62728:79"/> now <hi>forged</hi> ones, ſomething or other we muſt at leaſt, have heard of theirs, upon all the <hi>Emergent</hi> Controverſies and <hi>Difficulties</hi> that happen'd in the Church: In ſhort, We muſt have known of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the <hi>Popes</hi> of thoſe Ages, by the ſame methods we know of the Authority of the then <hi>Emperors,</hi> by their <hi>Actions,</hi> by their <hi>Laws,</hi> by their <hi>Reſcripts,</hi> by their <hi>Bulls,</hi> and by the whole Courſe of their <hi>Government.</hi> And therefore we muſt not judge of a thing of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by ſome few <hi>accidental</hi> and <hi>general</hi> Expreſſions in Authors, or by <hi>Compliments,</hi> which the <hi>Biſhops</hi> of ſo <hi>great</hi> a See could not eaſily miſs of.</p>
            <p>The <hi>last Argument</hi> I ſhall make uſe of is this, That it is not eaſily to be believed, that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> has left ſuch an Authority in his
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:62728:80"/> Church, without leaving at leaſt, ſome Rules about it; ſuch as <hi>how,</hi> and <hi>by whom</hi> the Perſon who is inveſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it is to be <hi>Choſen, how</hi> his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is to be <hi>executed,</hi> and what are the <hi>bounds</hi> and <hi>limits</hi> of it, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it has any <hi>bounds</hi> or no: Theſe are Matters of great conſequence, which have been the occaſion of a great many <hi>Schiſms,</hi> and might have been, or may ſtill be the occaſion of a great many more; Beſides, that ſo vaſt an <hi>Office</hi> without any ſet limits, is mighty apt to degenerate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Tyranny,</hi> and to betray Men into great <hi>Exorbitancies,</hi> to tempt them to leave the Simplicity of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, to Uſurp upon the Rights of other People, and to affect at laſt, a <hi>Secular Dominion</hi> inſtead of a <hi>Spiritual Office.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In fact, the want of ſome ſuch Rules to limit and confine his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority has made great differences in
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:62728:80"/> the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> about this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: <hi>Some</hi> ſay, he has a <hi>plenitude</hi> of Power; <hi>others</hi> ſay, that he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to the <hi>Canons</hi> of the Church; <hi>ſome</hi> ſay, that he is above a <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Council, others</hi> deny it; <hi>ſome</hi> ſay, that he has the <hi>Supreme Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> over all the World, not only in <hi>Spirituals,</hi> but alſo in <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals,</hi> that he has a Power to <hi>Erect</hi> Kingdoms, to <hi>give away</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, to <hi>deprive</hi> Princes of their Dominions, and to take away the Obligation of Subjects to their <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance; others</hi> there are, who ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>qualify</hi> this with <hi>diſtinctions,</hi> or elſe quite <hi>deny</hi> it; laſtly, <hi>ſome</hi> there are who ſay, that he is <hi>Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible,</hi> that what he <hi>ſolemnly</hi> deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines ought to be a <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Law</hi> to all Chriſtians, and to be taken as the Dictate of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> but <hi>many</hi> there are who <hi>deny</hi> this too; beſides all which, thereare
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:62728:81"/> many Diſputes about his Power of granting <hi>Indulgencies,</hi> his <hi>diſpenſing</hi> with <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Vows,</hi> and with the <hi>Laws</hi> both of <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Church.</hi> Theſe are Differences of great moment, both with relation to <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> and may car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Men as different ways as <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Darkneſs</hi> are different, or as different as <hi>Truth</hi> is from the moſt <hi>monſtrous Hereſies</hi> in the World. Thus if the <hi>Pope</hi> be not above a <hi>General Council,</hi> he may carry thoſe into a State of <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Diſobedience</hi> who believe he is; if he cannot diſpenſe with <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Laws,</hi> and <hi>Vows,</hi> he may car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thoſe into great <hi>Sins</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve he can; if he cannot <hi>Depoſe Princes,</hi> he may carry thoſe into <hi>Rebellion, Perjury, Murther,</hi> and all ſorts of <hi>Villanies</hi> who are led by him; and if he be not <hi>Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> as he pretends to be, God
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:62728:81"/> knows whither he may carry thoſe who follow him: And ſo on the other ſide, if he has all theſe <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives,</hi> they are in as much dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger who ſay, that he has not.</p>
            <p>If Chriſt had thought fit to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point a <hi>Head</hi> of his Church, I cannot imagine, but He would have given the Church ſome Rules about his Power, and the Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that was due to him: And I cannot but wonder how the ſame <hi>Church</hi> holds Perſons that are of ſo contrary Opinions in Matters of this conſequence: Let us only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that ſingle Point of the <hi>Pope's Infallibility;</hi> I have already ſhewed that thoſe who do believe it, muſt have a different <hi>Rule of Faith</hi> from thoſe who do not, becauſe his <hi>Determinations</hi> muſt be part of the <hi>Rule</hi> of their Faith, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, they muſt have a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:62728:82"/> 
               <hi>Religion,</hi> from thoſe who do not believe it. But that which I would inſiſt upon at preſent, is this, That for a Perſon to affirm himſelf to be <hi>Infallible,</hi> and to be appointed by God for the <hi>Supreme Guide</hi> and <hi>Conductor</hi> of the Faith of Chriſtians, ſo that whatſoever he ſhall <hi>ſolemnly determine</hi> muſt be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved true <hi>without examining;</hi> I ſay, for a Perſon to affirm this of himſelf, ſuppoſing it be falſe, is downright <hi>Hereſy,</hi> and that as <hi>groſs</hi> and <hi>dangerous</hi> Hereſy as almoſt any Man can fall into: Now to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate this, I would only propoſe one thing; Suppoſe <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of thoſe other Matters in which he differed from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> had affirmed only this one Point; That God had made him <hi>Infallible,</hi> and appointed him to be the <hi>Guide</hi> of all Chriſtians: Would this have made him a He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:62728:82"/> or w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d it not? There is no Queſtion, but they muſt ſay, this would have made him and all his Followers ſo, or if there be any worſe Name by which they could call them; for if he were in their Opinion, a Heretick for pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be the <hi>Head</hi> only of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Infallibility;</hi> How much more muſt the other have made him ſo? Now what is <hi>Hereſy</hi> in <hi>one,</hi> muſt be <hi>Hereſy</hi> in <hi>every body,</hi> ſuppoſing it <hi>equally falſe;</hi> for Hereſy is not made ſo by <hi>difference of Perſons,</hi> but by the <hi>Nature of Things.</hi> All therefore that believe the <hi>Pope</hi> not to be <hi>Infallible,</hi> muſt as much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this Pretence to be <hi>Hereſy</hi> in <hi>him,</hi> and his <hi>followers,</hi> as they would in the Caſe of <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. for the <hi>Matter</hi> is the ſame in both, and the Pretence ſuppoſed to be <hi>equally falſe</hi> in both, but muſt be
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:62728:83"/> much more <hi>dangero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in the <hi>Pope,</hi> becauſe more People <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e like to be <hi>ſeduced</hi> by him. That Reaſon which makes thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church who deny his <hi>Infallibility,</hi> yet not ſpeak, or think ſo ſeverely of it, as they would do of the ſame Pretence in another Man, is realy ſo far from excuſing it, that it aggravates the Matter, and makes it worſe and much more dangerous than it would be in any other: They do not ſpeak out, becauſe the Perſon who pretends to this Privilege, has great Authority among them, and is at the Head of their Church, whereas this is the very thing which makes ſuch a Pretence the more pernicious, that he has great Authority even with the <hi>whole Body</hi> of that Church, and has a very great Number of them, who ſay, That if he determines <hi>Vertue to be Vice, and Vice to be Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue;</hi>
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:62728:83"/> and the ſame, if he deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines <hi>Infidelity to be Faith,</hi> yet he muſt be followed. God knows how many People ſuch a one may carry with him into <hi>Hereſies,</hi> or <hi>Immoralities,</hi> or even to <hi>Hell</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Perhaps they think that God will take care of his <hi>Church,</hi> and will not ſuffer any thing of that kind to happen; but ſure they have little reaſon to expect ſuch a miraculous care over them, who encourage the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers</hi> in ſuch a <hi>peſtilent Hereſy,</hi> by living in Communion with him, and owning him for the Head of their Church. But beſides, how do they mean that God will take care of his Church, when he has ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered a Perſon, whom they own to be the <hi>Head</hi> of it, to fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch a dangerous Hereſy?
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:62728:84"/> Will God preſerve him, that he ſhall fall into no other Hereſies? How do they know that, or how can they expect it? If any thing puts a Man out of the care and protection of God, certainly ſuch a falſe pretence as that, is moſt likely to do it; And as for thoſe who will ſtick by ſuch a Perſon notwithſtanding they ſee the falſeneſs of his pretences, they have reaſon to expect, that God <hi>ſhould give them over to ſtrong deluſions,</hi> rather than take any extraordinary care of them while they are in ſuch a way.</p>
            <p>I have now done with what I <hi>at first propoſed</hi> to ſpeak to, And I cannot but hope that I have ſaid enough to give you juſt reaſon to comply with the Laws of your Country in theſe matters. This I am ſure of, that I have
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:62728:84"/> not willingly <hi>miſrepreſented</hi> any thing, or made uſe of any <hi>reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> which did not firſt <hi>convince</hi> my ſelf; If, in this ſhort <hi>Addreſs,</hi> I have not anſwered all the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in theſe matters, or if you deſire ſatisfaction in the other points of Controverſy betwixt us and your Church, I muſt renew my requeſt to you that you would conſult ſome of our <hi>Divines,</hi> or read ſome of thoſe <hi>Books</hi> which have been written upon the ſeveral <hi>Subjects,</hi> which I am perſwaded, can hardly fail of Convincing you, if they are read impartially. As for <hi>my ſelf,</hi> if I find by the ſucceſs of this, that any thing I can do, may help forward your Converſion, I ſhall be very glad to take any further pains in it; And in the mean time ſhall not fail to put up my
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:62728:85"/> Prayers to Almighty God on your behalf, that he would be pleaſed to take away all Prejudice, to open your Eyes, and bring you to the knowledge of the Truth.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:62728:85"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
